<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Capucin treated, or The lives of the Capucins with the life of S. Francis their patron. Wherein is described, and examined the original of the Capucins, their vows, rules, and disciplines. Written originally in French by the exquisite pen of that incomparably learned, and pious divine, Mr. Peter du Moulin, and Englished by Philanax Orthodoxus.</title>
            <title>Capucin. English</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215372</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827267</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1846:23; 2026:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Capucin treated, or The lives of the Capucins with the life of S. Francis their patron. Wherein is described, and examined the original of the Capucins, their vows, rules, and disciplines. Written originally in French by the exquisite pen of that incomparably learned, and pious divine, Mr. Peter du Moulin, and Englished by Philanax Orthodoxus.</title>
                  <title>Capucin. English</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 108 p. : ill. (frontis.)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Marsh, at the Princes Arms in Chancery-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing (2nd ed., 1994) D2582 on UMI microfilm "Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 2026.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Congregational Library, London ("Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 1846), and the Bodleian Library (reel 2026).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Capuchins --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31684:1"/>
            <p>THE CAPUCIN TREATED, OR, The lives of the <hi>Capucins,</hi> with the life of S. FRANCIS their <hi>Patron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is deſcribed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the Original of the <hi>Capucins,</hi> their Vows, Rules, and Diſcipline's.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in French by the exquiſite pen of that incomparably learned, and Pious Divine, Mr. <hi>Peter du Moulin,</hi> And Engliſhed By <hi>Philanax Orthodoxus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 4.8.</hi>
               </bibl> Bodily exerciſe profiteth little, but Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is profitable unto all things, having promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Marſh,</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31684:2"/>
            <head>To the truly vertuous (and therefore truly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) Lady, the Lady <hi>Catherine Colleton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F our labours ought to be dedicated to thoſe perſons to whom we are moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, then I am ſure, I am not miſtaken in addreſſing this ſmall tranſlation to your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And conſequently I had been guilty of injuſtice had I addreſſed it elſwhere. Beſides, had I let ſlip ſo fair an opportunity of publiſhing to the world my thankfulneſs for the many and great favours you have been pleaſed to confer on me, I had been guilty of ingratitude: which is ſo odious a vice, that certainly, it is inexcuſable in a Chriſtian. For the
<pb facs="tcp:31684:3"/> very Heathens by the light of nature have diſcovered ſo much of its ugli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the ancient <hi>Perſians</hi> were wont to ſay, <hi>If you call a man an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull perſon, you call him every thing that implies baſeneſs, and unworthineſs.</hi> But Madam, I know well enough, that the higheſt pitch of gratitude I am capable of, bears no proportion with the greatneſs of your favours: but I know withall, that where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe is to be had, your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will accept it inſtead of good pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; a mite or a talent being all one to you, whoſe goodneſs, regards not the quantity, or quality of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but the intention of the perſon that preſents it. Wherefore this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle dares promiſe it ſelf a gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception from your Ladyſhip, which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour if you ſhall be pleaſed to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe it, it needs not care what enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment it finds from others. I ſhall uſe no other argument to invite your Ladyſhip to the peruſal of it, than
<pb facs="tcp:31684:3"/> to tell you that the variety of its plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing divertiſements, may prove a good bulwark againſt the aſſaults of (your old enemy) melancholy: and if it does you that good ſervice, I ſhal think my pains in tranſlating it very happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtowed. I cannot conclude with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying my gratefull acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the worthy Gentleman your Husband, and to the hopeful young Gentlemen your Sons, for the many undeſerved civilities <hi>I</hi> have received from them: But they muſt give me leave to acknowledg my Obligations to your Ladyſhip in particular, and therefore to ſtile my ſelf more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your thankfull, and humble ſervant. <hi>P. O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:31684:4"/>
            <head>The Tranſlator to the Reader.</head>
            <p>EXperience tells us that exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple prevailes more then precept. And if ſo, then we may conclude that the mock-ſanctity of the <hi>Capucins</hi> (who for ſtrictneſs of Life carry away the Bell from all the other Orders of the Romiſh Church) hath gained many a proſelyte. But I dare promiſe (by the help of God) that no perſon ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by theſe Impoſtors, who will but take the paines to peruſe this ſmall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. For it plainly ſhews that their holineſs cheifly conſists in abſurd and extravagant actions, which render them more like Bedlams, and Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puddings, then Saints. And as for St <hi>Francis</hi> their Patron, who is ſo much cried up by the Romaniſts for his emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence in ſanctity, that they place him
<pb facs="tcp:31684:4"/> in Heaven amongſt the Seraphins; and ſome do ſo blaſphemouſlie compare him with Chriſt, that they ſay, it is queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable whether of the two was the typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Jeſus; and <hi>Turſellinus</hi> ſaith of him,</p>
            <p>Francis <hi>that was, ſhall now be Chriſt to thee;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Chriſt that was, St.</hi> Francis <hi>now ſhall be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, this grand Saint is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be a grand Cheat, and in effect nothing elſe but an ignorant, ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ridiculous Enthuſiaſt. But I ſhall not foreſtall the curioſity of the Reader, onely I ſhall ſay in commendation of the book, that it will pleaſe his humour if he be but ingenious.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:31684:5"/>
            <head>The Authors Preface.</head>
            <p>Some new gueſts being come to this Town, who are rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of modeſty, and ſincerity, common civility requires that we ſhould preſent them with ſomething, which may prove uſefull and ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them. Now I cannot think of a fitter preſent for perſons of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime profeſſion, and extraordinary ſanctity, then to preſent them with a deſcription of their Otiginal, and the continuation, and progreſs of their vertues. For although Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> in his book againſt my Three Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons calls me Fool, Cheat, and an Impoſtor, yet the Rule of Charity requires us to render good for evil. Beſides we muſt not judge of perſons by one ſingle action: neither muſt we, under pretence that this Reverend Father hath his fits of paſſions, conceal his vertues; Eſpecially, that <hi>Capucin</hi>-like goodneſs
<pb facs="tcp:31684:5"/> of his, when in his Sermon at the gallows, to comfort a whore who was to be executed, he calls her ſiſter; and why might not he call whores his ſiſters, ſeeing venerable <hi>Francis,</hi> the Patron of the <hi>Capucins,</hi> called the Magpies, Graſhoppers, and Swallows his ſiſters? With the like Prudence he exhorts this poor condemned perſon, whoſe name was <hi>Margaret,</hi> to recommend her Soul to St. <hi>Margaret,</hi> which is a Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t that never was in the world, and is placed in heaven without having ever been upon earth. After which proofes of his rare wit, he condemnes us all to hell, to keep him company. Wherefore he will not be offended, I ſuppoſe, if in acknowledgment of ſo charitable an office, I addreſs to him this ſmall treatiſe, wherein he will ſee the Original of his Order, and the illuſtrious actions of the <hi>Capucins,</hi> whoſe perfection the Apoſtles could not attaine unto. The Reader will
<pb facs="tcp:31684:6"/> here finde very pleaſant extravagances and Follies more then enough to make a Saint of (the word <hi>Saint</hi> having changed its ſignification in this bleſſed age:) For now a dayes if a man would attaine unto a Seraphique, and ſupereminent ſanctity, he muſt firſt be out of his wits.</p>
            <p>The enſuing Narrative would afford ſufficient ſubject for laughter, did it not afford much more ſubject for ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> compaſſion. For a man cannot ſee, without great grief, the Chriſtian Religion quite disfigured, and poor people fed with empty ſhews in ſtead of true and holy doctrines.</p>
            <p>The God of mercy take pitty on ſo many poor people ſo groſſely abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and ſtir up his zeal, and wonted compaſſions to deliver ſo many Souls enſnared by a counterfeit holineſs: to whom the holy Scriptures are a book altogether unknown, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with more then ſeven ſeales.</p>
            <p>My deſigne in this treatiſe is not to
<pb facs="tcp:31684:6"/> offend theſe Fathers, but to inſtruct them, and to ſhew them how farr diſtant they are from true holineſs, alſo to demonſtrate to them that in aſpiring to a degree of glory above <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and other ſuch petty Saints, who never did workes of ſupererogation, they take the courſe to come behind the meaneſt: and that ſome crimes are more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then their ſanctity. The Lord open their eyes that they may ſee it is a dangerous thing to mock him, and that they have to do with a terrible Judg, who cannot be deceived, who ſearcheth the heart, and from whom nothing is hid.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:31684:7"/>
            <head>A Table of the Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the Monaſtick profeſſion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. <hi>Chap. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the begging Fryars, and their vows: and of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and the Jeſuits. <hi>Chap. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the excellence, and prerogatives of each Order of the begging Fryars. <hi>Chap. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the words <hi>Minor,</hi> and <hi>Minime;</hi> and of the obſervation of the whole Rule. <hi>Chap. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the auſterity, and diſciplines of the Capucins; and firſt of their habit. <hi>Chap. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Divers auſterities and obſervations of the <hi>Capucins,</hi> as well thoſe to which they are obliged by their Rule, and by the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of their Order, as thoſe to which they oblige themſelves by voluntary devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Chap. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the whippings of the <hi>Capucins. Chap. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:31684:7"/>
               <item>Of the penances of the <hi>Capucins. Chap. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some extravagant actions in which the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucins</hi> place holineſs. <hi>Chap. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the names which the <hi>Capucins</hi> take at their entrance into this profeſſion. <hi>Chap. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the form of making their vow. <hi>Chap. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some obſervations upon this vow. <hi>Chap. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The impiety of the Superiours anſwer. <hi>Chap. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That corporal auſterities, and whipping, and tormenting of the body are not marks of holineſs. <hi>Chap. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the auſterities, and humilities of the <hi>Capucins</hi> are full of hypocriſie. <hi>Chap. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the pleaſant proceſs betwixt the <hi>Capucins,</hi> and the <hi>Recollects</hi> about the tip of their hoods. Alſo of Maſſes in green, red, and violet. <hi>Chap 16,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>By what means St. <hi>Francis</hi> obtained of Pope <hi>Innocent III.</hi> the approbation of his Rule. <hi>Chap. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the humility, and incomparable patience of <hi>St. Francis,</hi> and of his most notable acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Chap. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The great reward which St. <hi>Francis</hi> received for his humility. And of his marks. <hi>Chap. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:31684:8"/>
               <item>That under the Cloak of humility St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> hid an unparallel'd pride. <hi>Chap. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Laws, and ordinances contained in Saint <hi>Francis</hi> his Rule. <hi>Chap. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the holy Scripture is falſified, and wreſted in St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Rule. <hi>Chap. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of poverty, and riches. <hi>Chap. 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the vow of poverty, and of idle begging, and of works and ſatisfactions of ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. <hi>Chap. 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the fraternity of the Cord. An extract of a book entituled <hi>The Treaſure of the Indulgences of St.</hi> Francis<hi>'s Cord,</hi> tranſlated out of <hi>Italian</hi> into <hi>French.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Canonization of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius de Loyola. Chap. 25.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31684:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CAPUCIN TREATED, OR, The Lives of the CAPU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CINS, with the Life of St. <hi>FRANCIS</hi> their Patron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Monaſtique profeſſion in general.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Monks do generally profeſs works of Supererogation, that is, to do more good works, and more perfect, then thoſe which God commands in his Law; that is, they profeſs to do works more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then to love, and ſerve God with all their heart, and with all their ſtrength; for it is that which God commands in his Law.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31684:9"/> Therefore they ſerve God with more than all their ſtrength; they are more vertuous than God would have them to be. Moreover they would make us believe, that by their profeſſion of auſterity, and ſevere Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, they do more ſatisfactory works, and ſuffer more puniſhment than their ſins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and that the overplus ſerves for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For the Pope gathers this overplus into the Church-treaſury, and diſtributes it to people by his indulgences.</p>
               <p>By theſe works of ſupererogation the Monks pretend to attain unto a ſupereminent degree of celeſtial glory, far above thoſe ſmall Saints who contented themſelves to fulfill the Law of God, without doing any more. This degree of glory is called by the Doctors <hi>Aureola.</hi> To which degree <hi>Abraham, Jacob, Samuel, David, &amp;c.</hi> have not attained; for they never did works of ſupererogation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the begging Fryars, and their vows; and of the difference twixt them, and the Jeſuits.</head>
               <p>THere are four ſorts of begging Fryars, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Minors</hi> (called in <hi>France Cord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liers</hi>) the Preachers (who are alſo calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31684:9"/> 
                  <hi>Jacobins,</hi> and <hi>Dominicans</hi>) the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> and the <hi>Auguſtines.</hi> They bind themſelves by vow to three things. They vow poverty, ſo that they poſſeſs nothing in particular, although they abound in common. Alſo they vow never to marry This they call the vow of Chaſtity, as if there could be no chaſtity in a married eſtate. The third vow, is the vow of obedience, whereby they do not only oblige themſelves to keep the Laws of God, but moſt exactly to obſerve the Rule of that Saint who is their Patron, and the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Order, and to obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Guardian, or Superior of their Convent, and to obey the General of their Order, and above all the Pope.</p>
               <p>The Jeſuits beg not,<note place="margin">Ribaden ex vitâ Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſ, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and reject the auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the <hi>Minors,</hi> and will not be called Monks. They are well ſhod, warmly clad, and lie on good beds. And they that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Fathers (who are the chief of their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg) have their Table furniſhed with the choiceſt meats. They labour with very great induſtry to gather wealth, although <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> their Founder, did beg. They vow never to marry. But their chief vow, and which they obſerve moſt ſtrictly, is the vow of blind obedience, whereby they are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to obey their Superior in all that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31684:10"/> without enquiring whether the thing be good, or evil: for they will always have it preſuppoſed that the thing is good. This obedience hath coſt many Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces their lives, particularly, that excellent Prince <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Grandfathet to the Duke of <hi>Bovillon</hi> who was killed at <hi>Delft</hi> by <hi>Balthazar Gerard</hi> of the <hi>Franck</hi> County, excited thereunto by the Jeſuits of <hi>Treves.</hi> His proceſs and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation are to be ſeen at <hi>Delft</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They ſay indeed, that we muſt do nothing contrary to the commands of God; but they permit not thoſe who are commanded by the Superior, to examine whether his command be conformable to the commands of God. For (as Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the third, in the Bull which <hi>Ribadenera</hi> inſerts in the life of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> ſaith) <hi>Chriſtum in Praepoſito praeſentem agnoſcunt. They acknowledg Jeſus Chriſt to be preſent in the perſon of the Superior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Capucins are more moderate; for they oblige themſelves to obey their Superiour in all things except ſin. For example; if the Superior ſhould command a Capucin to plant Cole-worts with the leaves downward, and the root upward, or to lick up the ſpittle of another Capucin, or to plant a ſtraw, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to water it untill it grows, the Monk is bound
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31684:10"/> to obey theſe commands, ſuch actions being moſt proper to try the obedience of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the excellence, and prerogatives of each Order of the begging Fryars.</head>
               <p>EAch Order of the begging Monkes hath ſome priviledges and Prerogatives to render it recommendable. The <hi>Carmelites</hi> have this priviledg above the other Orders, that they remain in Purgatory but untill the next Saturday after their death.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Antonin,</hi> who hath written the life of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> the Patron of the Preaching Fryars, tells us, that St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> being once in a trance, ſaw the heavens opened, and a multitude of Monks in celeſtial glory, but ſaw not one of his own Order amongſt them, whereupon this bleſſed Saint wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly. But Jeſus Chriſt comforted him, by ſhewing him a multitude of <hi>Jacobin</hi> Fryars that were hid under the <hi>Virgin Maries</hi> kirtle.</p>
               <p>Not one of any other Order ever had this honour. It is obſervable that this <hi>Antonin,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Florence,</hi> was Canonized by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 7th. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1523. and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31684:11"/> that in the Bull of Canonization the ſaid Pope approves of, and authorizeth the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this <hi>Antonin,</hi> and gives great Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences to thoſe who ſhall viſit his reliques. The ſame is recited by <hi>Theodorick</hi> in the life of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> as <hi>Surius</hi> reports.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Minors</hi> ſurpaſs all the other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the greatneſs of their Indulgences, granted by the Popes to St. <hi>Francis's</hi> Order. Read a book entituled, <hi>The treaſure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Indulgences of St.</hi> Francis<hi>'s Cord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Printed at <hi>Rouen</hi> by <hi>Tho. Dare</hi> in the <hi>Jew's</hi> ſtreet, near the Palace, 1614.</note> and you ſhall find theſe words in p. 119. <hi>Item, every day untill the nativity of our Lady, there is eight hundred ſixty five thouſand, and one hundred ſixty two years, and one hundred days of indulgence, and a remiſſion of the third part of ſins, granted to divers Churches.</hi> The Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits laugh at this, and care not to obtain of he Pope ſuch Indulgences.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This may be ſeen in the book of the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of the frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Cord, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> by <hi>John le Bouc</hi> at St. <hi>Hillarys Mount.</hi>
                  </note>Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1586. on <hi>May</hi> 7, graunted to thoſe of the fraternity of St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi>'s Cord, who ſhall ſay five <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> &amp; as many <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> on Palm-Saturday, and on the feaſt of St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> and that before <hi>Porta Latina,</hi> the pardon of all their ſins, and power to free one ſoul out Purgatory. And theſe priviledges are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the letters Patents of the ſame Pope, dated at St. <hi>Marks. Aug.</hi> 9. 1587.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:31684:11"/>
               <p>But the moſt memorable Indulgence is that which (as the <hi>Roſary</hi> of <hi>Bernardin</hi> ſaith) St. <hi>Francis</hi> obtained for the Church of <hi>Sancta Maria Angelorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Francis</hi> was born in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is in the Dutchy of <hi>Spoleta.</hi>
                  </note> called <hi>Portiancula</hi> in the City of <hi>Aſſiſe (viz.)</hi> that all they who ſhall go into that Church ſhall receive the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all their ſins. However, Jeſus Chriſt would not grant this to St. <hi>Francis,</hi> but on condition that he ſhould get a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this Indulgence from the Pope.<note place="margin">Antonin. in vita Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minici c. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>1.</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſub Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daco Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit ut alterum baptiſmum <hi>Th. 2. 2</hi> q. ult. art. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; in <hi>4.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>4.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> art <hi>3.</hi> ſect. ad ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium. Bell. lib. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachis. c. <hi>8.</hi> ſect. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Eman. Sa. Aphor. in verb. Religio ſex alae. eorum ſunt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x perfectiones qui bus ornatus ſuit beatus <hi>Franciſcus.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>This alſo is one of the prerogatives of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Order, and of St. <hi>Dominick</hi>'s Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the habit of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> or St. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> is as good as a ſecond Baptiſm, and that by vertue of this habit all our ſins paſt are cancelled. And this is the reaſon why many Princes and perſons of quality on their death-beds have been clad in the habit of a <hi>Cordelier,</hi> or <hi>Capucin,</hi> that their ſins may be pardoned.</p>
               <p>Of all the Patrons of the Monaſtique Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders no one is exalted to ſo high a degree of celeſtial glory as St. <hi>Francis;</hi> (for he is placed in the higheſt degree of Angelical glory.) The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> makes nine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Angels differing in glory. The high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Order is that of the <hi>Seraphins.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31684:12"/> is the Order of the <hi>Cherubins,</hi> &amp;c. But St. <hi>Francis</hi> is placed in the Order of the <hi>Seraphins,</hi> above the <hi>Cherubins,</hi> as St. <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin</hi> tels us in the life of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> in the firſt Chapter, where he ſaith, that thoſe words of the 18. <hi>Pſalm, He rode upon the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, and did flie upon the wings of the winds, are ſpoken not only of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>but may alſo be applied to</hi> St. <hi>Francis, who is exalted above the Cherubins.</hi> And in the ſame Chapter, he ſaith, that <hi>the Six wings of the Seraphins are the Six perfections wherewith</hi> St. <hi>Francis was adorned.</hi> In this high degree of Glory, he ſees eight Claſſes of Angels, and all the Saints, farr beneath himſelf.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> a General of St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis's</hi> Order, and a Cardinal, ſaith the like, as I ſhall ſhew you hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De Verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſignif. in b. Aliud mite Cor, et docile, terra bona ſuſcepit, hoc eſt fratrum <hi>Minorum</hi> religio.</note>Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> 3. in the Decretal <hi>Exiit qui Seminat</hi> ſaith, that when Jeſus Chriſt ſpeakes of the fourth prrt of the ſeed which fell on good ground, by this good fourth part is meant the Religion of the <hi>Minors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame place, this Pope, commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poverty and perfection of St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> obſerves he had no bagg, and that he findes not thoſe actions of infirmity which were in Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Chriſtus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git etiam infima, ſicut interdum ut in ſugae paetet, &amp; in loculis.</note> who had two actions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31684:12"/> of infirmity <hi>(viz.)</hi> he had a bagg, and he fled. In theſe two things Holy <hi>Francis</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAp. IV.</hi> Of the words <hi>Minor</hi> and <hi>Minime;</hi> and of the obſervation of the whole Rule.</head>
               <p>THe Monks of St. <hi>Francis's</hi> Order are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Minors,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Leſs</hi> than others, in token of Humility. But there is ſprung up another Order of <hi>Monkes,</hi> whereof St. <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Paula,</hi> a <hi>Calabrian,</hi> is Patron, and <hi>Author.</hi> This Saint lived in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> 11. who dyed <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1483. The Monks of this Order not thinking it hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility enough to be called <hi>Minors,</hi> call themſelves <hi>Minimes,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>Least of all.</hi> The Life of theſe Monkes is altogether Quadrageſimal, that is a continual Lent; By vertue of this title they pretend a right to begging, becauſe Jeſus Chriſt in the 10. of <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall give to drink to one of the leaſt of theſe, or to one of theſe</hi> Minimes, <hi>a cup of cold water onely, ſhall not loſe his reward.</hi> However, this hinders them not from receiving an alms of wine, although Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks of cold water onely.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:31684:13"/>
               <p>It is obſervable, that in the Maſſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid St. <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Paula,</hi> which is cele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brated on the ſecond of <hi>April,</hi> the Prieſt reads aloud this verſe of the Goſpel: <hi>Quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> uni ex Minimis feciſtis, mihi feciſtis. Alle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luja. What you have done to one of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Minimes, you have done it to me.</hi> For the preſuppoſe that Jeſus Chriſt will ſpeak o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them in the day of the general Judgment This Maſſe, which is peculiar to the Orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Minimes,</hi> they have cauſed to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> printed.</p>
               <p>But to return to the Fryars <hi>Minors,</hi> ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are divers ſorts of them <hi>(viz)</hi> the <hi>Obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vantines,</hi> the <hi>Recollects,</hi> the <hi>Capucins, &amp;c</hi> There was a time when the <hi>Cordeliers</hi> onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were in requeſt; but afterward theſe <hi>Corde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liers</hi> giving themſelves liberty in dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> things, and diſpencing with themſelves fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the entire obſervation of St. <hi>Francis's</hi> Rule and of divers conſtitutions of the Order the <hi>Capucins</hi> ſprung up, who now a day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have the eſteem and admiration of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, profeſſing to obſerve the Rule entirel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> although they do it not. For the Rule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> St. <hi>Francis</hi> commands the Fryars <hi>Minors</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> labor with their hands, which command th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Capucins</hi> obſerve not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:31684:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Auſterity, and Diſcipline of the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins:</hi> and firſt of their habits.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Capucins</hi> go bare-foot, and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legg'd, onely they wear Sandals, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical ſhooes, which are nothing elſe but ſoles of ſhooes ſo tyed over the feet that the feet appear. They weare onely a Gown and a ſharp pointed hood: the other ſorts of Fryars <hi>Minors</hi> weare a round hood in forme of a Child's biggin.</p>
               <p>They weare no ſhirt s, onely they have drawers, which they let down when they whip themſelves. To weare two garments, or to have ſtockings, and ſhooes, or to be girt with a leather girdle, and not with a cord, is counted a mortal ſin. And yet the Legends of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> written by St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> St. <hi>Antonine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bonaven. apud Suri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pag. <hi>34.</hi> Antonin, pag. <hi>722</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Jacobus de Voragine,</hi> ſay that St. <hi>Francis</hi> did ſomtimes wear ſtockings and ſhooes, and was girt with a leather girdle.</p>
               <p>In this Cord the <hi>Capucins</hi> knit great knots for an Ornament. All this is done in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and there is great merit in it.</p>
               <p>They never put off their Garments ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31684:14"/> it be to take the vermine out of them, or to patch them. Yea they will in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty put patches on a new garment. Their garment conſiſts of three pieces, in honor of the Trinity: To be clad in the habit does a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much good as Baptiſm: I have ſeen in the houſes of Princes, and Gentlemen of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, little Children of ſix or ſeven years old clad in Capucins habit. Mothers do this, to imprint on their Childrens hearts a love and reverence to the Order of St. <hi>Francis.</hi> If a Capucin ſhould die without his Cord, he would be eſteemed to have dyed without St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s habit, and an evil cenſure would be paſt upon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Divers auſterities, and obſervations of the Capucins, as well thoſe to which they are obliged by their Rule, and by the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of their Order, as thoſe to which they oblige themſelves by voluntary devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>BY the conſtitutions of the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars, to ride on horſ-back, except in caſe of ſickneſs, or urgent neceſſity, is a mortal ſin; although St. <hi>Francis</hi> did often ride upon an Aſs.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:31684:14"/>
               <p>It is alſo a mortal ſin for a Monk to have in particular, and without the Superior's knowledg, any thing worth above thirty pence: and if he ſhould die without revealing it to the Superior, he is deprived of Eccleſiaſtical burial. You may ſee this in the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Rule.</p>
               <p>They are not permitted to be Godfathers, nor to preſent a child to baptiſm: this they account ſcandalous, and St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Rule forbids it.</p>
               <p>It is an ordinary cuſtom among the Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins, to ſend to women in travel, little pieces of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s wood, or to cauſe them to ſwallow the powder of it in ſome holy water, to facilitate their delivery. This St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi>'s wood is the wood of a great Oak, which was once the ſtaffe which he uſed when he walked abroad. This ſtaff (out of reverence) he would not carry into the Church, but pitching it into the ground at the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door it took root, and became a great tree.</p>
               <p>In the Choire of the Capucin's Churches there ſtands a veſſel full of ſand, or lime, into which they ſpit. Divers Capucins who have left the Order, and have been eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes, do aſſure me that they have ſeen ſome Capucins lick up the ſpittle which (through heedleſneſs) hath faln beſide the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31684:15"/> veſſel, and in mortification to ſwallow it. This is accounted a great vertue. They have alſo ſeen the Superior command ſome Monks to lick up the ſpittle of the reſt, in humility, and mortification.</p>
               <p>It is a frequent cuſtome among the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucins, to prick themſelves, and with thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blood to ſign vows to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and to carry the papers whereon theſe vows are written, about with them. This is taken fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grand devotion.</p>
               <p>They lie in their cloaths upon boards, and a little ſtraw, over which there is a linnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth ſpread, and nailed to the boards.</p>
               <p>They make three Lent: two by neceſſity of precept, and the third by voluntary devotion. This St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Rule teacheth them. Alſo they faſt twelve days before <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> and on all the Vigils of the Virgin, of the Apoſtles, and of the Saints of their Order.</p>
               <p>They give to whom they pleaſe, certain Letters, which they call Letters of <hi>Filiation,</hi> authorized by the Pope, whereby they give to thoſe who have them, as great a ſhare of all their auſterities, penances, faſts, whippings, &amp;c. as if they were members of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. So that a Merchant or a Gentleman, by virtue of theſe Letters of <hi>Filiation</hi> hath as real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31684:15"/> a part in their merits and ſatisfactions, as if they were his own, for ſo they ſay God will have it, and that he takes this for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>They never go out of the Convent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out asking leave of the Superior on their knees.</p>
               <p>The young Monks dare not ſpeak to the elder, but on their knees; and when they have ſpoken, they make a very low bow.</p>
               <p>The Capucins give to people little tickets, wherein the name of Jeſus is written, to cure the <hi>Ague</hi> or <hi>Fever.</hi> Herein they differ from the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Monks, who give a little loaf without leaven on St. <hi>Nicholas Talen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi>'s day, who was a Saint of their Order. They ſuppoſe that theſe loaves have a great vertue againſt diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Their Conſtitutions forbid them to ſhave themſelves with a Raſor, but they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to trim themſelves with Sciſſars. And they dare not keep a Raſor in their Convents, except it be to ſcarifie their ſhoulders after the uſe of cupping-glaſſes.</p>
               <p>By the ſame Conſtitutions they are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the uſe of ſpices; and to beg eggs, and cheeſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:31684:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Whippings of the <hi>Capucins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY the Conſtitutions of the Order, the Capucins whip themſelves three time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a week, at two a Clock after midnight, <hi>(viz.)</hi> at two after Sunday night, after Tueſday night, and after Thurſday night. In the winter they whip themſelves at half an hour paſt five in the evening, for fear of too great a cold in the night. They whip themſelves on the back and buttocks.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bonav. vitae <hi>Franciſci</hi> pag. <hi>38. Antonin. 3</hi> parte Chro. tit. <hi>24.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> ſect. <hi>1.</hi> Quod vir Dei ſentiens veſte depo ſtia, chord â duriſſimâ ſe verbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, dicens, Eja frater a ſine, &amp;c.</note>This they do in imitation of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> of whom St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> and St. <hi>Antonine</hi> write, that being one day tickled with carnal temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, he laſht himſelf very ſeverely with his Cord, ſaying thus to himſelf: <hi>Eja frater aſine, decet te manere, &amp; ſic ſubire flagellum;</hi> that is, <hi>Go to, brother aſſe, thou muſt ſtay, and be whipt thus.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibi. Sed cùm tentatio nequaquam diſcederet, foras exiens cùm hyems eſſet in magnam nivis congeriem ſe nudum immerſit, &amp;c. <hi>Antonin.</hi> tit. <hi>24.</hi> cap. <hi>2,</hi> ſect. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> But his temptations conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for all this, and therefore, to ſubdue them, he ſtript himſelf ſtark naked, and plunged himſelf over head and ears in the ſnow, and made ſeven ſnow-balls, ſaying,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31684:16"/> 
                  <hi>The biggeſt is thy wife, and theſe two are thy two daughters, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame is recited by <hi>James de Voragine</hi> in his Legend of St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</hi> And St. <hi>Antonine</hi> ſaith, that he often plunged himſelf in a place full of ice and ſnow, <hi>uſque ad illiciti motus receſſum,</hi> that is, untill the immodeſt motion of his ſecret parts ceaſed.</p>
               <p>Beſides this whiping,<note place="margin">Antonin. c. <hi>1.</hi> Suſtinuic multa fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gella à dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monibus, &amp;c.</note> and the torments which St. <hi>Francis</hi> inflicted on his own body, the devils whipt him often, and very rudely: but the bleſſed Saint gave demonſtrations that he received all this with joy. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaith, that one day the devils beat him ſo ſorely that they left him half dead.<note place="margin">Bona. apud Surium <hi>p. 40</hi> &amp; <hi>41.</hi> Daemones verbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquunt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But to returning to the whipping of the Capucins, before they begin this pleaſant exerciſe, each one prepares himſelf for it, and with his whip drives his fellow to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient diſtance from him, for fear of ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him. Being all ready, the Superior knocks with his hand on a bench, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently all the candles are blown out, and he that wears the cope that week begins to ſing the Pſalm <hi>Miſerere,</hi> and they all follow, whipping themſemſelves while they ſing. Then they ſing <hi>De Profundis,</hi> then the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Salve Regina,</hi> and then the ancient <hi>Chriſtus factus eſt obediens pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nobis.</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31684:17"/> all this ſinging (which laſts about half an hour) the whipping continues in ſuch ſort that the blood trickles down. And they make a terrible noiſe with their whips The ſinging being ended, the Superior knock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his ſeat with his foot, and ſo the whipping ceaſeth.</p>
               <p>This diſcipline is very terrible; for many times you ſhall ſee the place all bloody and in great Convents where there are 60 or 80. Capucins, there is ſuch a noiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Monks ſinging with open mouth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their whips clack, that you would thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the houſe were falling. This whipping is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſt action, for theſe fathers deſerve it well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>In the holy week they uſe this diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every day, but they redouble it on Good-fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, for on that day inſtead of one <hi>Miſerer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> they ſing three, and the whipping continue all the while.</p>
               <p>On the Vigiles of the feaſts of our Lady and of the other ſolemn feaſts, and on ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> friday of the month of March they, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves in the dining-room before din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But this whipping laſts no longer tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> while they are ſinging of one <hi>Miſerere,</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the 51. Pſalm, which ends in <hi>vitulos</hi> Hence comes the proverb to be whipt fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Miſerere</hi> unto <hi>vitulos.</hi> This whipping, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:31684:17"/> is milder, and ſhorter than at other times, is exerciſed on the ſhoulders onely, and not on the buttocks.</p>
               <p>This being ended, they eat bread and pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage on their knees in honour of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Their night whippings are exerciſed on their buttocks; but the day whippings on the ſhoulders only.</p>
               <p>In the morning theſe poor Capucins go abroad to beg, with carved buttocks and embroidered backs, carrying a Wallet on the ſhoulder. They beg from door to door; one gives them bread, another a ſhoulder of Mutton, another a Leg of a Capon, another puts ſome Wine into their bottle, which is very large, and of a great capacity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Penances of the Capucins.</head>
               <p>THe penances of the Capucins, for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of a fault, are impoſed in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-room, which place ſerves alſo for a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe.</p>
               <p>In this place before dinner the Monks on their knees wait for the ſuperior, or Guardian; who being come, the moſt ancient of thoſe who are to receive penance, puts off his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31684:18"/> from his ſhoulders, claſps his hands, and holds down his head, as low as his knees, accuſing himſelf of ſins committed againſt the Conſtitutions. They do not accuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for want of a firm affiance in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpel: but ordinarily thoſe things which the penitent confeſſeth, are tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles; for, he confeſſeth either that he hath talked too loud, or walked too faſt, or gaz'd about too much, or hath ſcratcht himſelf while he was at prayers, or hath broken an earthen pot, or the like. This confeſſion they call <hi>the fault.</hi> Then come the reſt, and make ſuch another confeſſion.</p>
               <p>As theſe confeſſions are abſurd, ſo are the penances impoſed by the Superior on the penitent as ridiculous. He that is accuſed in the Chapter-houſe to have broken ſilence, is condemned to take a ſhort ſtaff in his mouth, and to hold it betwixt his teeth until the Superior ſay to him, <hi>It is enough.</hi> In Italian he ſays <hi>Baſta.</hi> Somtimes they have a long pole, which five or ſix of them hold between their teeth, and ſo walk up and down with it while the others are at dinner, who muſt take heed that they do not laugh.</p>
               <p>If any one hath whipt himſelf too gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is condemned to whip himſelf publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the ſhoulders with a fox-tail in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31684:18"/> preſence of thoſe that are at dinner.</p>
               <p>If any one hath talked too much, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to draw a Croſs on the ground wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h his tongue.</p>
               <p>Sometimes for a penance they make a Monk eat with a Cat in the ſame diſh. And others are made to ſuck a flint dipt in vinegar.</p>
               <p>Others riſe from their knees to drink, and as often as they drink they ſay to their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren who are at dinner, before they drink, <hi>Brethren, pray to God for poor brother</hi> Linotte, <hi>or for brother</hi> Tribouleus, <hi>or for poor brother</hi> Griboville, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For they are obliged to take ridiculous names in humility, to render themſelves contemptible. After this they drink by permiſſion with very great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty.</p>
               <p>If any one be accuſed of being too ſpruce and finical, a bucket of water is brought him to view himſelf in, or they preſent him with the backſide of a kettle for a looking-glaſs.</p>
               <p>They who have ſlept at prayers, are made to lie down in the preſence of thoſe that are at table, and are made to ſnore, as if they were aſleep.</p>
               <p>If any breaks a cup, or bottle, or a frying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan, he is made to carry it about hanging at his neck for a pennance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31684:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Some extravagant actions, in which the Capucins place holineſs.</head>
               <p>DIvers <hi>Capucins</hi> who have left the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, have confeſſed to me, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were accounted the moſt zealous amongſt them, yet they had much adoe to forbear laughing at ſome extravagant actions, in which the <hi>Capucins</hi> place holineſs.</p>
               <p>Theſe things following are practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To view themſelves in a Fryingpan. To make a croſs with the tongue in the aſhes. To combe the beard with a rake. To chop off the beard on a block with a hatchet. To ſtand upon one legg in the midſt of the dining-room. To kiſs the feet of all thoſe who are at dinner. To make a Monk dance before them all. To make him fence. To blindfold him with a dirty clout. To go about upon all four like a beaſt. To carry about on the head a basket like a head-piece. To put upon the noſe a pair of ſpectacles made of felt. To ride about upon a ſtick like a child, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the abſurdeſt penance of all is, when the Superior commands a Monk, who having
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31684:19"/> filled his belly, leaves ſome part of his dinner behind him, to eat it up all, So that he muſt break his belly in humility, and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
               <p>In the life of St. <hi>Felix de Cantalice,</hi> (an almes-begger at <hi>Rome,</hi> Canonized by the Pope, about 16 or 17 years ago) this is put amongſt his vertuous actions that being at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the ſtreet he met <hi>Philip de Neri,</hi> founder of the Prieſts of the Oratory, and made him drink off his bottle, and that <hi>Philip</hi> in requital put his hat on <hi>Felix</hi> his head: Whereupon the Children in the ſtreet cryed out <hi>Fra Felice a un capello.</hi> Thus did theſe Saints by a great ſelf denial mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally communicate their holineſs to each other.</p>
               <p>In the Chronicles of St. <hi>Francis's</hi> Order, it is recorded, that Fryar <hi>Juniperus,</hi> (who is Canonized for a Saint) boiled a hen with her guts, feathers and all. And that being in a certain Caſtle, he left his dung in the bed where he lay. Another Fryar <hi>Minor,</hi> named <hi>Jacobo,</hi> in humility leapt into a houſe of office.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:31684:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the names, which the Capucincs tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when they enter into this profeſſion.</head>
               <p>WHen the <hi>Capucins</hi> enter into the Order, after the year of Probation they take another name then that which they had given them at their Baptiſme: For (as I have already ſaid) St. <hi>Francis's</hi> habit is accounted another Baptiſm. One is called <hi>Hilary,</hi> another <hi>Joſeph,</hi> another <hi>Baſil, &amp;c.</hi> Some of them take Sublime and Caeleſtial names. One is called Father <hi>Angel,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father <hi>Archangel,</hi> another Father <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> another Father <hi>Cherubin,</hi> another Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Seraphin, &amp;c.</hi> which names are very unſuitable to the profeſſion of humility. To be a Fryar <hi>Minor,</hi> that is, to be <hi>the leaſt,</hi> and yet to be an Archangel, are things altogether inconſiſtent. Beſides the nature of their vow is to do works of Supererogation: but the Angels do no ſuch works, for they content themſelves with obeying the commands of God.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who ſay the Capucins are called Angels becauſe they imitate the Angels, in that they marry not, nor receive mony, do
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31684:20"/> great wrong to the Order of theſe Monks; for by the ſame reaſon they may be ſaid to imitate the Devils, becauſe they neither mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor poſſeſſe wealth any more than the Angels.</p>
               <p>It is a mockery to ſay, that they are called Angels, and Seraphins, becauſe they take the Angels and Seraphins for their Patrons, and Protectors: For by the ſame reaſon a marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed woman, who hath taken the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> for her Patroneſs, may be called the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> And he who takes God for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, may be called God. But ſith the <hi>Capucins</hi> have St. <hi>Francis</hi> for their Protector, who is (as they ſay) of the Order of the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins,</hi> and exalted above the eight Orders of Angels, what need have they to take the Angels for their Patrons? Beſides, they who chooſe Angels, or Saints for their Patrons, chooſe one certain Angel, or Saint for their Patron; and not the Angels and Saints in general.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The form of making their Vow.</head>
               <p>WHen a <hi>Capucin</hi> will enter into the Order, after the year of probation, he is admitted to make the vow, which is done
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31684:21"/> in the preſence of the Superior, and his bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren, in theſe terms:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do Vow, and promiſe to God the Father Almighty, and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>to the Bleſſed Apoſtles</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>to the Bleſſed St.</hi> Francis <hi>my Patron, and to you my Father, to obſerve the Rule of the Fryars</hi> Minors, <hi>living in Poverty, Obedience, and Chaſtity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>He that receives this Vow anſwers,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I, if thou obſerve it, do promiſe thee, in the name of God, life eternal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAp. XII.</hi> Some obſervations upon this Vow.</head>
               <p>Divers things are remarkable in this vow, which being rightly underſtood, we ſhall finde that many abuſes, yea impieties are therein covered with the cloak of religion.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, this vow is made to God the Father, to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to Saints, and to the Superior of the Convent, without making any mention at all of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:31684:21"/>
               <p>In the Second place, he who makes this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow to Saints departed, preſuppoſeth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe Saints do ſee him, and that they know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he intention of his heart. This is contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Holy Scripture, which ſaith, that <hi>the dead have no more a portion for ever in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing that is done under the Sun. Eccleſ.</hi> 9.6. And that <hi>God onely knows the hearts of the Children of men.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.30.</p>
               <p>This vow is repugnant to all the examples contained in the Holy Scriptures, wherein there is no vow made to creatures, but to God onely; as God himſelf commands in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.14. <hi>Offer unto God thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and pay thy vows unto the moſt High.</hi> Here ſacrifices, and vows are linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as things equally due unto God. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> holds that we muſt offer ſacrifices to God onely. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that in the holy Scripture not one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is to be found of vows made to Saints, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> freely confeſſeth in his book <hi>De cultu Sanctorum,</hi> Chapter 9. in theſe words; <hi>When the Holy Scriptures were written, the cuſtome of making vows to Saints was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun.</hi> The ſame Jeſuit in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaith that <hi>a vow is an action of religion due to God onely, even as ſwearing, and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing are, as appears by the holy Scriptures.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:31684:22"/> Theſe are his own words. <hi>Thomas Aquin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the Prince of School-men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thomas</hi> 2.2. <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt.</hi> 28. <hi>art.</hi> 5.</note> ſaith the ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>A vow</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is to be made to God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, but a promiſe may be made to a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> And in the ſame place, <hi>A Vow is an act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Religion, or Divine Worſhip.</hi> Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> in his notes up this place of <hi>Thomas,</hi> to defend vows m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Saints, ſaith, that the Saints are Gods, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that vows are made to them, <hi>ut ſunt Dij <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> participationem,</hi> as they are Gods by parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pation. The ſame ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> afore-mentioned chapter. <hi>A Vow belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not to the Saints but onely as they are Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> participation. But we are certaine that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Saints who raigne with Chriſt are ſuch.</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> go <hi>&amp;c.</hi> According to what Pope <hi>Gregor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2. ſaith in his Epiſtle to the Emperour <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (viz.)</hi> that <hi>all the Kingdomes of the We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> owne St.</hi> Peter <hi>for a God upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe Doctors conſider not, that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vow be a worſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi> and due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God onely, and that if we make vows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Saints becauſe they are Gods by participation it follows that we give to Saints the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Latria</hi> by participation.</p>
               <p>Alſo they conſider not, that by the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaoſn it may be ſaid, that the Superior, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Guardian, who receives this vow, is God to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:31684:22"/> by participation. For when the Fryar <hi>Minor</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath ſaid, <hi>I vow unto God, and to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in, and to the Saints,</hi> he adds, <hi>and to you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny Father,</hi> vowing to the Guardian in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me termes in which he vows to the Saints, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to God. This needs not ſeem ſtrange; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Prieſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re called Gods and Creators of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, having a Divine power, yea, a power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Jeſus Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Beſte,</hi> a famous Preacher, in his book of the Prieſtly-Office, chap. 3. ſaith, <hi>The Prieſt-hood and the Deity have I know not what of common, and are almoſt of an equal grandeur, for they have the ſame power.</hi> Item. <hi>Seeing that the Prieſt-hood is equal to the Deity, and that all Prieſts are Gods, therefore it far exceeds the Kingly Office, and Prieſts are much more than Kings.</hi> And a little after he ſaith, that <hi>God obeys the Prieſts as often as they pronounce the words of conſecration.</hi> A Sorboniſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Petrus Aurelius,</hi> hath lately written a book with the approbation, and by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Colledge of <hi>Sorbon,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes a treatiſe of the Jeſuits entituled <hi>Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia;</hi> and in the 75 page this <hi>Aurelius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Data eſt Sacerdotibus poteſtas Chriſtum, hoc eſt Deum ipſum producendi,</hi> that is, <hi>A power is given to Prieſts to produce Chriſt, that is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31684:23"/> to ſay God himſelf.</hi> He adds, that <hi>the power o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Prieſts hath in it a certain emulation of the eternal operations, whereby the Divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are produced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Qui crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit me (ſi fas eſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere) dedit mihi creare ſe; &amp; qui creavit me creatur me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainte me.</note>
                  <hi>Gabriel Biel,</hi> famous among the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in his firſt Leſſon upon the Canon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Maſs ſpeaks thus; <hi>The Prieſt hath grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> power over both the bodies of Chriſt.</hi> That is over the Church, and over the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hoſte, which he calls God. And in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fourth Leſſon, Whoever ſaw the like? H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that created me (if I may ſo ſpeak) hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> given me power to create him. And he that created me without my help, is create<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by my means.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Simeon Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelmenſis lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Chro. Vigner</hi> in his Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>p.</hi> 300.</note>This manner of ſpeech is not new. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1097. <hi>Urban</hi> II. called a Council a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> IIII. and all other ſecular Princes who ſhould claim a right to the inveſtiture of Biſhops and Abbots, and to the Collations of Benefices, and Prebends, alledging that <hi>it is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing that thoſe hands which create God, ſhould be obliged to ſo much ignominy as to do homage to thoſe hands which night and day are defiled with filthy and diſhoneſt touches.</hi> Wherefore, you muſt not wonder, if a Monk that is admitted into the Order, makes a vow to the Superior, who is a Prieſt, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31684:23"/> gives him that honour, which belongs to the worſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi> ſeeing the Prieſts are called Gods, and Creators of their Creator, and that they have a power over Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>To theſe teſtimonies of the Doctors of the Romiſh Church, who ſay, that a vow belongs to the worſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi> and ought to be made to God only, we muſt adde the teſtimony of that Jeſuit, <hi>Cardinal Tolet.</hi> in Book 4. Of the inſtitution of Prieſts, chap. 17. <hi>A vow is a promiſe made to God by a deliberate purpoſe and will.</hi> By theſe things it appears, that a vow made to Saints, or to a Superior of a Convent, is pure Idolatry; for thereby that honour which is due to God only, is communicated to the creature.</p>
               <p>Our adverſaries cannot eſcape by ſaying, that in vowing to Saints they vow mediatly to God; for the worſhip of <hi>Latria</hi> ought not to be given to the creature either mediately or immediately. In all worſhip of <hi>Latria</hi> we muſt addreſs our ſelves to God directly. The Monk that makes this vow addreſſeth himſelf to God directly by ſaying, <hi>I vow to almighty God, &amp;c.</hi> Having thus addreſſed himſelf to God directly, what need is there that he ſhould afterward addreſs himſelf to him mediately, and by oblique ways? It
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31684:24"/> is certain, that he who ſays to his Superior, or Guardian, <hi>I Vow to you my Father,</hi> ſpeaks not to God, and by theſe words vows not to God. Conſider the words of this vow, and you ſhall find, that a Monk who is admitted into the Order, ſpeaks to God, to the Saints, and to his Superior in the ſame terms, and vows not in two different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p>But when <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth that the cuſtome of making Vows to Saints was not begun when the holy Scriptures were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, he ſhould have mentioned the time when it began, and not have cheated the Reader with falſe allegations, as his uſual manner is. For he alledgeth theſe words of <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his 13. book of Evangelical preparation, chap. 7. <hi>Honouring the ſouldiers of true piety as the friends of God, we come to their monuments and make vows to them;</hi> Which paſſage is falſe, and altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>He alſo alledgeth <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his 8. book againſt the Greeks, which book is falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attributed to <hi>Theodoret.</hi> In one point <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> beſides his error, diſcovers his ignorance in the Greek tongue, in not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Greeks have no proper word to expreſs the word <hi>Vow:</hi> And the Latine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31684:24"/> Interpreter, to whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> truſts, hath falſly tranſlated <hi>Votorum rei dona perſolvunt,</hi> Which words are not in the Greek Text of the book attributed to <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is in honour of the Pope that the Monks vow to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and not to St. <hi>John,</hi> and St. <hi>James:</hi> for they make the two former the Founders of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The things to which this Monk obligeth himſelf, are poverty, chaſtity, and obedience. Of poverty I ſhall ſpeak hereafter. As for chaſtity, the Jeſuit <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> in his Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms upon the word <hi>votum</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the vow of Priesthood is not a vow of chaſtity, and that the Biſhop can diſpence with it;</hi> Whereupon we demand, whether a Monk or a Prieſt that commits fornication, doth not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the vow of Chaſtity, and whether by this Vow he doth not oblige himſelf not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit fornication. If he doth not oblige him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to it, he ſhews that he will not be obliged by vow to obey the command of God, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery:</hi> But by this vow he only obligeth himſelf to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from a thing which God permits, and not from that which he forbids. But if this Monk by vowing Chaſtity vows not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit fornication, it is evident that by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting fornication he violates his vow, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31684:25"/> beſides he tranſgreſſeth the command of God, which obligeth us much more than any vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary vow. So that he commits two evils, <hi>(viz.)</hi> He breaks his vow, and violates the law of God. Why then, when a Monk or Prieſt marries for fear of violating the Law of God by committing fornication, is he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to have committed a greater ſin than when he commits fornication? Why then is not a Prieſt that commits fornication, made irregular, and incapable of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; but if he marries is preſently degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yea, and declared puniſhable with death? To this they anſwer, that it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath broken his vow, and yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains unpuniſhed, and ceaſeth not to ſing Maſs for all that. For the commands of God do not bind ſo ſtrongly as voluntary vows do, which are made without, yea contrary to the word of God, which ſaith, <hi>If they cannot contain, let them marry.</hi> And <hi>to avoid forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, let every man have his own wife, and let every woman have her own huſband,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.</p>
               <p>But that a Prieſt who commits fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea hath divers Concubines, is not thereby rendred irregular, and incapable of the Prieſt-hood, not onely experience ſhews (examples of this being numberleſs) but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31684:25"/> we have alſo the determination of Pope <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the III. Thereupon in the firſt book of the <hi>Decretals,</hi> in the twelfth Title, in the Chapter <hi>Quia circa,</hi> His words are theſe, <hi>Thou deſireſt to be inſtructed by the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique See, Whether Prieſts that have divers concubines, ought to be counted bigamous. To which we think fit to anſwer, that ſeeing they have not incurr'd the irregularity of bigamy, thou mayest diſpence with their exerciſing of the Prieſtly Office, they being ſtained only with ſimple fornication.</hi> But for marrying of one wife, according to the Apoſtles rule, a Prieſt is degraded, yea puniſhed with death.</p>
               <p>But, which is much more, one that is a notorious Sodomite, is not made irregular, but may ſing Maſs for all that: as <hi>Navarre,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Navarr.</hi> in caput ad inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. <hi>23.</hi> queſt. <hi>2.</hi> De defenſione proximi.</note> the moſt knowing of all the Canoniſts, and the Popes Penitentiary teacheth; <hi>A man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth not incur irregularity but for the caſes ſpecified in the law, of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Sodomie is none.</hi> And this he proves by the authority of Pope <hi>Innocent.</hi> And he adds, that in <hi>Italy, (which is more troubled with this evil than it ſhould be) they demand no diſpenſation for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In fine, how binding ſoever the vow of not marrying may be, yet the Pope can
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31684:26"/> diſpence with it, and may permit a man to marry contrary to his vow. <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> in the ſame place ſaith, that the Biſhops may alſo diſpence with this vow, and permit a man to marry.</p>
               <p>Methinks alſo to vow to St. <hi>Peter</hi> never to marry, is to pretend to be wiſer than he; for he was a married man. It is juſt as if one ſhould ſay to him, <hi>I do vow to thee not to follow thy example. I do promiſe to be wiſer and holier than thou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is evident, that he who burns with fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy luſts, and yet vows never to marry, does like a ſick perſon that ſays to God, <hi>Lord, I am ſick, but I promiſe thee that I will not make uſe of the remedies which thou offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me, and haſt ordained in thy word, for I will be wiſer thaen thou.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:31684:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The Impiety of the Superiours Anſwer.</head>
               <p>IF there be Superſtition and Impiety in this Vow, whereby a Monk vows to the Creature, and obligeth himſelf to things which God commands not; yea, to things which he forbids: there is no leſs in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which the Superiour or Guardian makes him, ſaying;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I, if thou keep this vow, do promiſe thee, in Gods name, life Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words duely conſidered, will make a man ttemble for fear. For one that is neither ſent, nor authorized by the King, comes to a man, and ſayes, <hi>I have order from the King to promiſe you ſuch a Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if you do ſuch a thing,</hi> is a Cheat, and a perfidious perſon, and deſerves to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, becauſe he ſpeaks without order, and without being ſent by the King. But the Superiour, who makes this promiſe to the new Monk in God's name, cannot ſhew his Commiſſion or Warrant from God for the making of this promiſe. He abuſeth the poor Monk, by making him believe that he is ſent by God to make him this promiſe in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31684:27"/> Gods name, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That if he lives in beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, if he never marries, and if he be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Guardian of his Convent, he ſhall have Eternal life: For, theſe three things are things which God commands not in his Word, and to which he hath made no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; yea, theſe are obſervations whereby God is more often offended then ſerved: Theſe are things which a Heathen or Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite may do. But to ſerve God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Word, and to believe in Jeſus Chriſt as he is propoſed to us in the Goſpel, are things to which God hath promiſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life, and cannot be done by any, but by thoſe that are the true Children of God: Theſe are things, for which the Superiour ſhould ſay, (not I promiſe thee, but) God promiſeth thee Eternal life. For a man ought not to promiſe that which he cannot give.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> That corporal Auſterities, and Whippings, and tormenting of the body, are not marks of Holineſs.</head>
               <p>HE is very much deceived, who takes the ſeveritie and torments which a man inflicts on his body, for proofs or ſigns of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31684:27"/> Holineſs. The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. ſaith, <hi>Bodily exerciſe profiteth little; but god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is profitable unto all things, having the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> All that the <hi>Capucins</hi> do, is nothing,<note place="margin">1 K n. 18.28.</note> in compariſon of what <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts did: for they did cut and mangle their bodies with knives, and imbrued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in blood, for the ſervice of their Idol. There are <hi>Mahometan</hi> Monks called <hi>Dervis,</hi> who live very auſterely, and do even roaſt their bodies upon the hot ſcalding ſands, and with buckles and rings of Iron make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves incapable for generation. The <hi>Cynick</hi> Philoſophers did beg: <hi>Diogenes</hi> lay in the ſtreet in a tub, having no other houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuff then a woodden diſh; and yet he brake that too, when he conſidered thar Nature had given him one in the hollow of his hand. Read <hi>Apulejus</hi> his eighth Book of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſians,</hi> and you will there ſee the deſcription of the Prieſts of the <hi>Syrian</hi> Goddeſs, who did cut and ſlaſh their bodies.<note place="margin">Arrepto flagro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didem ſe multimodis mulctat ictibus. Avidis amimis corradentes omnia, &amp; in ſacculos huic quaeſtui de induſtria praeparatos, farcientes.</note> He deſcribes one of thoſe Prieſts, that did whip himſelf with a whip full of knots, being armed with obſtinacy againſt the ſmart of the ſtrokes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the blood ſtreamed down his body. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31684:28"/> he adds,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That when theſe Prieſts had done whipping themſelves, they went about a begging, and one gave them a piece of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, another Wine, another Cheeſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Alms they put into Wallets. In a word, the deſcription which he gives of theſe mad Prieſts, doth very much reſemble the lives of the <hi>Capucins. Lucian</hi> in his Book, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>The Aſs,</hi> deſcribes theſe Prieſts after the very ſame manner.</p>
               <p>It is a grand abuſe to make Piety conſiſt in things wherein Chriſtians may be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Heathens. There is a proud humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which deſpiſeth it ſelf, that it may be valued by others. The Apoſtles, and their Diſciples, did not live ſo: In a ſimple and ordinary habit, and manner of life, they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſoberly, and laboured in the work which God had committed to them. They were famous, not for their extravagant and hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apparel, not for whipping themſelves, nor for eating pottage on their knees; but for their zeal, and holineſs of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:31684:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> That the Auſterities, and Humilities of the Capucins are full of Hypocriſie.</head>
               <p>WE may eaſily know what to think of the Abſtinences, Whippings, and humilities of the <hi>Capucins, (viz.)</hi> that in the midſt of their Auſterities they diſcover their pride. And of this I'le give you ſome examples.</p>
               <p>Before the <hi>Capucins</hi> begin their Lents (for they have three Lents) they feaſt and make merry for a whole week, during which time, there is no frolick or Jovial act, which they omit. Some of them ſing ſongs of good fellowſhip, others ſing Amorous, or love ſongs, others ſhew <hi>Hocus pocus</hi> tricks, others ſtand upon their heads, or act the Tumbler or Juggler, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In fine, every one doth ſuch things as he had learned before he was a Monk.</p>
               <p>In great towns there be few <hi>Capucins</hi> but have their ſuperſtitiouſly devout women who furniſh them with all ſorts of dainties, as ſweet meats, comfits, gellies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that ſome <hi>Capucins</hi> have more choice of dainties in their Cels then Ladies have in their clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:31684:29"/>
               <p>When a <hi>Capucin</hi> comes from abroad, warm linen clothes are put on his body, his feet are waſhed with ſweet herbs, and when they are wiped with warm napkins, every one comes and kiſſeth them.</p>
               <p>Many of the old Monks, who are called <hi>Fathers of importance,</hi> are ſo carefull of their health, that they have a cook for themſelves in particular (who is alwaies a Monk) a groom of the chamber, and an Apothecary, who follow them from Convent to Convent. You ſhall ſee very few of theſe Fathers of importance, ſick but they are very impatient if they want but the leaſt trifle, and then all the town is ranſackt from one end to the other, to find what they would have. The Nuns furniſh them with ſweet meats, the Ladies with rare broths and gellies, the Gentlemen of the Country with wild fowle, the merchants and other townſ-men with Shambles-meat; and the wine which they ordinarily drink, is the beſt that is to be had. Thoſe <hi>Capucins,</hi> who, to ſave their Souls, have left the Order, do proteſt that they have learned of us how to faſt; and that when they were <hi>Capucins,</hi> they fed more highly, and lived more pleaſantly and plentifully.</p>
               <p>In great Convents of <hi>Capucins</hi> ſuch as are at <hi>Paris, and Roven,</hi> a moſt furious am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31684:29"/> and envie diſcovers it ſelf: For, to obtain the leaſt preferment in the Convent, and to ſupplant their competitors, they have their creatures who cry them up every where, and rail on thoſe that aſpire to the ſame. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; whence great diſorders do oftentimes ariſe; for Princes do more patiently bear contempts and injuries then the <hi>Capucins.</hi> And at the Tables of Dukes, Marqueſſes, and Earls, the <hi>Capucins</hi> ſuffer themſelves to be placed at the upper end.</p>
               <p>Their pride appears in this, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs works of ſupererogation, that is to ſay, better works then God commands: ſo that God may ſay to a <hi>Capucin, I would not have thee ſo holy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame ſpirit of pride appears in their calling themſelves <hi>Angels, Archangels, Spirits, Seraphins</hi> and <hi>Cherubins.</hi> It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo by the unworthy ſubmiſſions which the principal <hi>Capucins</hi> require of the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who never ſpeak to the Superiours but on their knees; which Superiours command them very baſe things, as to lick up the others ſpittle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It cannot be ſaid, that they wear a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and extravagant habit in humility and mortification; For, he that will ſubdue his Fleſh, may do it as well under a common
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31684:30"/> habit; he may under a uſual habit wear a hair-ſhirt, and may whip himſelf ſecretly as often as he pleaſeth, and without any one's knowledge: But this wild habit, differing from that of other men, ſerves onely to be look'd upon, and admired; for people gaze upon and admire nothing but what is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary.</p>
               <p>To this we may add, that he who makes profeſſion of ſimplicity and humility in his converſation, ſhould not be vain in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, nor too wantonly nice and delicate in his words, for fear of belying his Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by his Language.</p>
               <p>I ſpeak this becauſe of Father <hi>Joſeph,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Capucin;</hi> who in his new Book ſhews, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he hath made a great proviſion of Elegancies. As when he calls St. <hi>John, The Secretary o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Love to the Son of God.</hi> And of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantion</hi> he ſaith, that <hi>it is Love's Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece.</hi> And ſpeaking to us, he ſaith, That <hi>when God ſhall have brought us into his Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellar, there to taſte of the exceſs of his love, we ſhall not find it ſo difficult to believe, That Jeſus Chriſt did eat himſelf, and that toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Chriſt's body the Devil entred into Judas.</hi> With the like grace, ſuppoſing the words of St. <hi>Philip</hi> to the Eunuch too weak and impertinent, as they are ſet down in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31684:30"/> eighth Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> he introduceth him ſpeaking thus; <hi>Sir, will it pleaſe you that I preſume to ask you a queſtion, with all due reſpect?</hi> To which he makes the Eunuch anſwer with the like civility, <hi>I pray oblige me ſo much as to come into this Coach.</hi> Note alſo, that the very firſt word of his Book is a miſtake, beginning thus, <hi>The Apoſtle St. Philip;</hi> For this <hi>Philip</hi> was not an Apoſtle. With the like vanity he talks of preaching in a Ruff, and in a Band, and of yellow and green Gentlewomen; and he brings in ſpeaking I know not what Courtier, who praiſeth and extolleth him to his face, ſaying, That Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſpeaks very gracefully, and that all the Catholiques have been very much comforted by his Sermons, and do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the force and clearneſs of his Reaſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of the pleaſant Proceſs betwixt the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins</hi> and <hi>Recollects,</hi> about the Tip of their Hoods. Alſo of Maſſes in Red, Green, and Violet.</head>
               <p>THe pride of the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars did never more clearly appear, then in the quarrel which they had, and have to this day, with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31684:31"/> the <hi>Recollects,</hi> who are alſo of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Order. When we ſpeak of a Proceſs about nothing, we ſay, It is a Proceſs about the point of a needle; but the Proceſs of theſe <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars hath been about the point or Tip of their Hood.</p>
               <p>We muſt know, that the <hi>Cordeliers,</hi> who brag as well as the <hi>Capucins,</hi> that they wear St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Habit, differ from the <hi>Capucins</hi> in wearing a round Hood, and laugh at the <hi>Capucins</hi> and <hi>Recollects</hi> for wearing a ſharp-pointed Hood, calling it in deriſion,<note n="*" place="margin">Made like a Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, in which they put ſuch things as they ſell by retail.</note> 
                  <hi>A Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers paper.</hi> Betwixt theſe <hi>Capucins</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collects</hi> there began, a few years ſince, a great Proceſs in the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins</hi> complained, That the <hi>Recollects</hi> wore their Hood too long; and that thereby they would make themſelves equal to the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cins</hi> in Holineſs. That by reaſon of this long point, being equal in length to that of the <hi>Capucins,</hi> many are deceived, taking a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect</hi> for a <hi>Capucin,</hi> and ſo give him as much honour; although the <hi>Recollects</hi> are not to be compared to the <hi>Capucins</hi> for holineſs, and merit of Converſation. And therefore they requeſted, that by the Decree of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the <hi>Recollects</hi> might be condemned to ſhorten the point of their Hood.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Recollects,</hi> on the other ſide, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31684:31"/> and do ſo ſtill maintain, that they are not inferiour to the <hi>Capucins</hi> in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and perfection; and that it is no diſhonour to the <hi>Capucins</hi> if ſomtimes a <hi>Recollect</hi> be taken for a <hi>Capucin,</hi> or a <hi>Capucin</hi> for a <hi>Recollect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This proceſs hath cauſed great ſtirs, and hath much troubled theſe two Orders, and divided the Prelates of <hi>Rome</hi> into contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry factions. And it was pleaſant to hear the conteſts of theſe <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars. The <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucin</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Recollect, What! thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be equal to us in holineſs: Thou art ſo ambitious, as that thou wouldeſt be taken for a Capucin.</hi> But the <hi>Recollect,</hi> being witty in biting jeſts, ſaid, <hi>Thou thinkſt that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs conſiſts in wearing a long</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Ut priùs dictum eſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Grocers paper. Thou thinkeſt by thy pride to put the Holy Ghoſt into a long</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">through which they ſtrain their infuſions when they make ſyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups; it is a long ſharp-pointed bag.</note> 
                  <hi>Apothecaries bagg. The holineſs of you Capucins appears in this, vsz. That for eight days before Lent, you ſhew tricks of Legerdemain, and play the Tumblers,</hi> &amp;c. Thus did theſe Saints diſpute, quarreling which of them by their pride ſhould carry away the prize of humility.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Cordeliers,</hi> who wear a round hood like a childs biggin, took great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in beholding this ſtrife, and laughed at them both: For they ſay, that the hood of the old pictures and ſtatues of St. <hi>Francis,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:31684:32"/> hath not a long point; And they ſay, that their round hood, made in form of a child's biggin, is conformable to what our Saviour ſaith in the 18. Chap. of St. <hi>Matthew, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye become as little Children,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſſ. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ye cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdom of God. Caſſian</hi> ſaith the ſame of the <hi>Anchorites,</hi> living in the deſerts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that they wear a hood in imitation of the ſimplicity and innocency of Children, according to that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the 131. Pſalm, <hi>I am not haughty, but am even as a child weaned from his mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaks againſt this hood, and laughs at it: for obſerve what he ſaith of it, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Euſtochius, There are ſome</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who wear a hair-ſhirt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cucullis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brefactis ut ad infanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am redea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, imitantur noctuas, &amp; hubones.</note> 
                  <hi>and making themſelves hoods, to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble children, they are like Owls, and buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards.</hi> Afterward he adds, <hi>Shun thoſe whom thou ſeeſt have a Goat's beard, a black cloak, and that go with their feet naked, being har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with the cold: All theſe things are markes of the devil. When they have intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves into great men's houſes, they deceive ſilly women laden with ſin, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit a dejected gravity.</hi> This is a very fair leſſon for the <hi>Capucins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to this great proceſs: the <hi>Capucins</hi> did at laſt obtain ſentence in their
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31684:32"/> favour; for they had on their ſide one of the Popes near kinſmen, who was a Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin. By this ſentence of the Pope, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collects</hi> were condemned to ſhorten the tip of their hood: but they openly proteſted, that they would not obey this ſentence, ſaying, That they would rather diſſolve their Order, and relinquiſh all, then acquieſce in this ſentence. Wherefore yet to this day, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of the Pope, they wear their hood of the ſame length as before.</p>
               <p>Of this hood, as of the reſt of the habit of the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars, it is obſervable, that it is not lawfull for a Monk to change it in the leaſt, not ſo much as in the colours of the Maſs: For it is not lawfull to ſing Maſs in a red habit, on thoſe daies on which it is appointed to be ſung in a green habit; nor to be ſung in a black habit, on thoſe days on which it is appointed to be ſung in a violet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit: The rules in this caſe are very ſtrict,<note place="margin">pag. 328.</note> and are placed at the beginning of the Maſs-book.</p>
               <p>But Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> wrongs us in his new book, by endeavouring to prove that the like things are done amongſt us, objecting againſt me, that I wear a Ruff, and that as there are Maſſes in green, violet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo it may be ſaid, that amongſt us there are Sermons in a Ruff, and Sermons in a Band,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31684:33"/> Sermons in a Gown, and Sermons in a Cloak: for this <hi>Minor</hi> Fryar knows well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that we have no rules to oblige us to wear a Ruff or a Band, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath inviolable laws concerning Maſſes in green, red, and violet. It is to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that when St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> were in a gay humour, they ſang Maſs in a green habit. My deſign in mentioning the colours of Maſſes ſo ſtrictly enjoined, is to ſhew, that falſe religions having corrupted the true doctrine, do endeavour to colour this wickedneſs with a multitude of ceremonies, and external obſervations, in which great myſteries are pretended: So our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries having deſtroyed the body of true piety, pay the people with variety of colours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> How St. <hi>Francis</hi> obtained of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, the approbation of his Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRancis d' Aſſiſe,</hi> when he was but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſon, little known, and followed by none; moreover, being eſteemed out of his wits by his fellow citizens, who threw dirt at him, and alſo by his father, named <hi>Peter Bernardo,</hi> who did beat him, and kept him priſoner a long time, compoſed a Rule,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31684:33"/> and ſome laws, to the Obſervation whereof he would oblige thoſe who would believe him, promiſing them life eternal.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this Rule could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without the Popes approbation, and authority, he went to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. to beg the confirmation of his Rule. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris,</hi> an Engliſh Monk, Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the higheſt degree, and an admirer of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> in his Hiſtory of the life of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the III. ſaith,<note place="margin">pag. 237.</note> that the ſaid St. <hi>Francis</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelf to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the III. ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Conclave, and gave him his Rule in writing, intreating him to authorize it by his approbation: but Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> taking notice of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s bad cloaths, his dirty and contemptible countenance, his long beard, and the black hair of his eye-brows hanging down over his eyes, deſpiſed him, and ſaid to him, <hi>Go brother, and wallow in the dirt with the Swine, for thou art more like them than like a man.</hi> Which words as ſoon as <hi>Francis</hi> heard, he bowed himſelf very low, and in obedience to the command of his Holineſs, went and wallowed with ſwine in a puddle, wherein he tumbled ſo long that he was covered with dirt from head to foot; and in this pickle he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and preſented himſelf to the Pope,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31684:34"/> ſaying, <hi>My Lord, I have done what you commanded me,</hi> Whereat the Pope being very much aſtoniſhed, and admiring his great obedience, granted his requeſt, and approved of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Rule which is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved at this day by the <hi>Capucins,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars, with a grand obedience. This approbation was granted <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1212. as St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> and, St. <hi>Antonine</hi> teſtifie. And this approbation was again confirmed by Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> ſucceſſor to <hi>Innocent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of the humility, and incomparable patience of St. <hi>Francis;</hi> and of his moſt notable actions.</head>
               <p>DIvers have written the life and actions of St. <hi>Francis. Vincent</hi> in his <hi>Mirrour of Hiſtory</hi> writes it at large. <hi>Matthew Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> an Engliſh Monk, in the life of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Third, deſcribes the actions of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> and ſets down his Rule. Theſe two Hiſtorians wrote about thirty years after St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s death. <hi>James de Voragine</hi> hath written his Legend. We have alſo the Chronicles of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> upon the ſame
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:31684:34"/> ſubject. But the Authors of greateſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are firſt St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> a General of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Order, and a Cardinal, who wrote about forty years after St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s death. This <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> placeth amongſt her Saints, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Doctors. This is that St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> who compoſed the Pſalter of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure,</hi> was print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>Claude Chapelet,</hi> in St. <hi>James</hi>'s ſtreet at the ſign of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn, <hi>anno.</hi> 1601.</note> containing one hundred and fifty Pſalms, which are nothing elſe but the hundred and fifty Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> out of which <hi>Bonaventure</hi> hath taken the word <hi>God,</hi> and hath put the word <hi>Virgin</hi> in its ſtead; for example, he thus begins the 109. Pſalm, (which according to the Hebrew, is the 110) <hi>The Lord ſaid unto our Lady, ſit thou at my right hand, &amp;c.</hi> And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. inſtead of, <hi>He that dwelleth in the ſecret place of the moſt High,</hi> he hath put, <hi>He that dwelleth in the help of the Mother of God.</hi> And in the 129. Pſalm, <hi>Out of the depths have I cryed unto thee, O our Lady, hear my voice.</hi> And ſo throughout the Pſalms. By this means the true honour which all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans owe to the holy, and bleſſed Virgin, turns to her reproach, by transforming her into an Idol, and by putting her in the place of God. This is that St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> to whom the <hi>Capucin Joſeph</hi> would have us give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:31684:35"/> and would have us believe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of S. <hi>Francis</hi>'s life, which he gives us.</p>
               <p>After this St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> we have St. <hi>Antonine,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Florence,</hi> Canonized by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Seventh, <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1523, with the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of his Doctrine, and great Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences granted to thoſe who ſhall ſhall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit his Sepulchre. I ſpeak this, becauſe no body may think that ſuch paſſages as I ſhall quote out of theſe Authors, are things which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not; or that I have invented them; or that they are forged by perſons of ſmall authority. I alledge ſuch Saints as are prayed unto, and adored in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Francis</hi> his Father was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Peter Bernardo,</hi> A Citizen of <hi>Aſſiſe,</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Spolete</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Francis</hi>'s name, when he was young, was <hi>John Bernardo,</hi> but he chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his name, and would be called <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> becauſe he ſpake French when he was moved by the Holy Ghoſt to utter the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God; as <hi>Bonaventure</hi> tells us, in the life of St. <hi>Francis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Life, written by St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> you may find in <hi>Surius,</hi> in the month of <hi>October.</hi> p. 30.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:31684:35"/>
               <p>When he was but young, and a Lay-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he demonſtrated a grand Humility, even to the kiſſing of Lepers: and one day alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his horſe to kiſs a Leper, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto him, that this Leper was <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His fellow-Citizens ſeeing him a greaſie and dirty fellow, and that he did wild and extravagant actions, judged him to be out of his wits; and running after him, threw ſtones at him, and covered him all over with dirt. Which when his Father ſaw, he fetcht him home, and kept him ſhut up a long time, whipping him cruelly, as mad folk are whipt for their cure. But his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taking pity on him, did, in the abſence of her Husband, ſet him at liberty.</p>
               <p>When his Father returned home, he brought him before the Biſhop, and made him diſclaim his right of Inheritance: To which <hi>Francis</hi> very willingly conſented; yea, pulling off his Breeches, and the reſt of his cloaths, he made himſelf ſtark naked, being (as St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaith) drunk with the Holy Ghoſt. Then he ſaid to his Father, <hi>Hitherto I have called thee my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but henceforward I will ſay, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in Heaven. Antonine</hi> reports the ſame in the Life of St. <hi>Francis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:31684:36"/>
               <p>Being thus naked, he went into a Spittle where Lepers were kept, and tended them, kiſſing their feet, and wiping and kiſſing their ſores with an admirable devotion, as St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> tells us.</p>
               <p>In thoſe dayes St. <hi>Francis</hi> wore ſhooes, and walked with a ſtaff, and girded himſelf with a leather-girdle: But afterwards, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this equipage exceſſive, and too deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, he left his ſhooes and his ſtaff, and in humility girded himſelf with a Cord.</p>
               <p>Being tempted with unchaſt deſires, he plunged himſelf over head and ears in a ditch full of ice. And one day, the Devil having breathed on him, he felt the fire of carnal luſt kindled within him: Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this bleſſed Saint ſtript himſelf ſtark na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and whipt himſelf terribly with his Cord, ſaying, <hi>Eja frater aſine, decet te ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, &amp; ſic ſubire flagellum;</hi> that is, <hi>Go eo, brother aſs, thou muſt ſtay there, and be whipt thus. Antonine</hi> and <hi>James de Voragine</hi> report the ſame.</p>
               <p>The hard ground was his ordinary bed, and a ſtone his pillow. But one day, by reaſon of a pain in his head, taking a feather-pillow, and repoſing himſelf thereupon, the Devil got into it, and extremely troubled his brain, and diſturbed his devotion: At
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31684:36"/> which St. <hi>Francis</hi> being incenſed, took hold of the pillow, and threw away both it and the Devil.</p>
               <p>Finding that his carnal concupiſcence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, he ran to his garden, and gathering a great heap of ſnow, he plunged himſelf in it over head and ears, ſtark naked, as St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaith. But St. <hi>Antonine</hi> ſaith, that he plunged himſelf in it onely ſo high as his privities. Then he made ſeven ſnow-balls, ſaying of one, <hi>This is my Mother;</hi> and of another, <hi>This is my Daughter,</hi> &amp;c. whereupon the Devil went away very much aſhamed.</p>
               <p>He preſented his Rule to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third; who for a while rejected it, and ſome of the Cardinals oppoſed it, ſaying, That it propoſed novelties, and things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be done: But at laſt, St. <hi>Francis</hi> wallowing in the mire with Swine, obtained his requeſt.</p>
               <p>Sometimes he had a mind to hear himſelf reviled;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonavent.</hi> p. 39. <hi>Legenda Antonin.</hi> p. 725. <hi>Legenda.</hi>
                  </note> and to this purpoſe he once ſaid to a Monk, <hi>Rail on me.</hi> Which ſtrict command the Monk not daring to diſobey, ſaid to him, <hi>Thou art an idle, lazie Lubber, a mercenary fellow, an ignorant ſott, and a worthleſs raſcal.</hi> Whereat St. <hi>Francis</hi> greatly rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, anſwered, <hi>God bleſs thee, my Son;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31684:37"/> for what thou haſt ſaid is vory true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonavent.</hi> pag. 39. <hi>Antonin.</hi> pag. 726.</note>One day he had a mind to feed bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then ordinary; for which reſolving to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſatisfaction, as having committed a great ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he cauſed himſelf to be dragged to the Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lows, with a halter about his neck, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> body naked, only he had a pair of Drawe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on; and there ſtanding on a great ſtone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confeſſed that he was a glutton, a fleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eater, and moſt worthy of ſcorn and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt. St. <hi>Antonine</hi> ſaith, that a Monk we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before him, crying aloud, <hi>Friends, beho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> this glutton, this eater of Pullets fleſh, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he hath eaten ſecretly without our knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonavent.</hi> pag. 41. The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend ſaith the ſame.</note>The Devils whipt him ſo cruelly, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they left him half-dead. And one day multitude of Devils running on the top <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his houſe with a horrible noiſe, he called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them with a ſweet and pleaſing voice, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> treating them to come down, and to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and torment him; ſaying to them, <hi>Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and avenge me of my adevrſary, which is my fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Legend. pag. 72.</note>Not being content with the torments the Devils inflicted on him, he whipt himſelf cruelly, taking delight in this exerciſe. And once he hid himſelf in a Cave a whole month, without any ones knowledge, as St. <hi>Antoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> teſtifies.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:31684:37"/>
               <p>St. <hi>Antonine</hi> and the Legend put this amongſt the proofs of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s holineſs;<note place="margin">pag. 721. <hi>Antonin. Tit.</hi> 24 <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>ſ.</hi> 2.</note> That being once at dinner at an honeſt mans houſe, a Capon of ſeven years old was brought to the table, and that he ſent a leg of this Capon for an Alms to a poor paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who was a<note n="*" place="margin">One that believes amiſs. <hi>Legenda Antonin.</hi> pag. 725. <hi>Bonavent.</hi>
                  </note> miſcreant, and a perverſe fellow. But the next day, when St. <hi>Francis</hi> was in the Pulpit preaching, this miſcreant, thinking to jeer St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſaid to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>I will ſhew you what ſort of meat</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis <hi>uſeth to feed on:</hi> and then going to ſhew the people the Capons leg, he found it turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Fiſh; whereupon this miſcreant was much confounded.</p>
               <p>When any one gave him roaſt-meat, he dragged it through the aſhes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antonin.</hi> pag. 726.</note> or laid it a ſoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in cold water, for fear of breaking his Vow of poverty and abſtinence. An inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, when they were eating the Paſſeover, did not think of.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Antonine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Antonsn. in vitâ S. Franciſci, <hi>pag. 723.</hi>
                  </note> that St. <hi>Francis</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Diſciples into three Companies; whereof two ſpent their time in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the third in action. This third ſort of Monks were called <hi>Pinzocgori,</hi> and were permi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to marry.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:31684:38"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Legenda Jacobi de Voragine. Antonin. p. <hi>724.</hi>
                  </note>Some Greek Monks having prepared dinner for him, when he came to the houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſaw clean linnen and glaſſes on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> table, he preſently got to the door, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ran out into the ſtreet, where meeting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beggar who had a very bad hat, he took th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hat, and putting it on his own head, ſat down at the door of the houſe, begging.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Legenda Jacobi de Voragine Antonin. in vitâ Franciſci.</note>Being weary, he got up upon an aſſe but having with him one <hi>Leonard</hi> a Monk who was on foot, this <hi>Leonard</hi> grumble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at it; which St. <hi>Francis</hi> perceiving, alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the aſſe, and ſaid to <hi>Leonard; Bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther get up upon the aſſe, for thou art of better a family than I.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Legenda Antonin.</note>He honoured Prieſts ſo much, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid, <hi>If I ſhould meet together on the way a Prieſt, and a Saint that came down from heaven, I would firſt go and kiſs the Prieſt's hands, and would ſay to the Saint, ſtay thou there a while.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The</hi> Legend <hi>and</hi> Anto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nin. p. <hi>726.</hi> &amp; <hi>727.</hi> Bonavent. p. <hi>44</hi> &amp; <hi>50</hi>
                  </note>In humility he preached to the birds. And being once in a Caſtle called <hi>Albian,</hi> while he was preaching to the people, a multitude of Swallows flockt about him; which by their ſinging hindred the people from hearing him: W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>upon turnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Swallows, he ſaid, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ters, ye ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> talked enough, now it is hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> time for me
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:31684:38"/> to ſpeak.</hi> At which words the Swallows were ſilent untill the Sermon was ended. And pittying a Hare,<note place="margin">Bonavent. page <hi>44.</hi>
                  </note> which ſuffered it ſelf to be taken, he ſaid to it, <hi>Brother Hare, why didſt thou ſuffer thy ſelf to be ſo deceived?</hi> A live Tench was preſented to him,<note place="margin">Antonin. page <hi>727.</hi> Bonavent. page <hi>44. The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend.</hi> Bonavent. pag. <hi>44.</hi>
                  </note> on which taking pitty, he threw it again into the River. Hearing a Graſhopper ſing, he ſaid to it, <hi>Sing, ſiſter Graſhopper, and praiſe the Creator with rejoicing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being in the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> called <hi>Portiuncula,</hi> ſome body gave him a ſheep, to which he gave inſtructions; and the ſheep in obedience to him, preſently ſell a bleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, while the Monks were ſinging in the Choir: and this creature did very humbly kneel down when the hoſte was held up. Whereupon <hi>Surius</hi> puts in the Margin, <hi>O that hereticks would learn henceforward to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Euchariſt!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Travelling through the Marquiſate of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cona,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antonin. p. <hi>727.</hi>
                  </note> he met on his way a Country fellow carrying two Lambs to Market to ſell them, which did bleat moſt pittifully; Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Francis,</hi> being touched with bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly compaſſion, ſaid to the Country fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>Why d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt thou torment my Brethren ſo?</hi> The Country man anſwered, <hi>I carry
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:31684:39"/> them to the Market to ſell them to ſome body that will eat them.</hi> Then the holy man ſaid to him, <hi>God forbid; rather take the cloak which I have on my ſhoulders.</hi> So he gave him his cloak, and ſaved the lives of his brethren, which he carried away on his ſhoulders with a brotherly Charity.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antonin. pag. <hi>727.</hi>
                  </note>Remembring that it is written in the two and twentieth Pſalm, <hi>I am a worm, and no man,</hi> he would not ſuffer a worm to be troden upon.</p>
               <p>One of his Monkes having ſpoken ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what roughly to a poor man, he commanded him to ſtrip himſelf, and to go ſtark na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before this poor man, and to kiſs his feet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antonin. in vitâ Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſci cap. <hi>2.</hi> ſ. <hi>6.</hi> Bonavent. page <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note>He was very devoutly preſent at a Chriſtmaſs mid-night Maſs, to which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cuſtome of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe days, and uſed ſtill in ſome places, an Oxe, and an Aſſe were led, and hay was carried for them.</p>
               <p>It is obſervable that <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Francis</hi> had no learning,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 48.</note> nor knowledg of the holy Scriptures, acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red either by ſtudy or inſtruction from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but that by the irradiation of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:31684:39"/> the eternal ſplendour, he penetrated e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the very bottome of the Holy Scripture. Hence it is, that in his Rule he alledgeth Scripture ſo dexterouſly, and pertinently, as we ſhall ſee anon.</p>
               <p>At laſt brother <hi>Francis</hi> dyed, having acted a Comedy both before God and man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:31684:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> The great rewards which St. <hi>Francis</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for his humility: And of his marks.</head>
               <p>A Humility ſo profound, and of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great a merit, was not unrewarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> St. <hi>Antonine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 728.</note> in the life of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ports, That the people did run after him and did tear his cloathes in pieces, every on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtriving to carry away a piece, believing tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe rags were of great vertue, and a prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meanes for ſalvation; ſo that the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> left him half naked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaith, That a certain holy ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had a viſion, wherein it ſeemed to him, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a golden croſs came out of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mouth, whoſe top touched Heaven, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its two armes reached unto the ends of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Earth.</p>
               <p>In the ſeventh chapter of the <hi>Revelati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> St. John</hi> ſpeaks thus; <hi>I ſaw another Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſcending from the Eaſt, having the ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the living God.</hi> St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life of St. <hi>Francis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonavent.</hi> pag. 31.</note> ſaith, That we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieve that without doubt this Angel is St <hi>Francis:</hi> theſe are his words; <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation) another Angel aſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31684:40"/> from the Eaſt, having the ſeal of the living God. Whence we gather, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible faith, that this meſſenger of God, beloved of Chriſt, to be imitated by us, and admired by the world, is that ſervant of God, Francis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pag. 40.</note> that a certain holy, and devout man, being once in St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s company, fell into a trance, and ſaw in Heaven divers ſeats, amongſt which he ſaw one more Magnificently adorned then the reſt, glittering with pretious ſtones, and very glorious: And as this holy man was wondering for whom this ſeat was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, a voice came to him from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>This was the ſeat of one of the lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Angels, and is kept for the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Francis. The Legend ſaith the ſame: and we have already ſeen, that this was the ſeat of one of the apoſtate Seraphins; and that by this exaltation the moſt humble <hi>Francis</hi> is placed above the Archangels, and above the Cherubins, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly above all the Saints, except the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> who is called The Queen of Heaven.</p>
               <p>All, that have written the life, and actions of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſay, That about two years before his death, God intending
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:31684:41"/> to recompence the humility and merits of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſent a Seraphin to him; which, lying upon him croſs-wiſe, imprinted on his hands and feet the marks of the wounds of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>After his death, there was a great ſtir, and conteſt about theſe marks: Some laughed at it, and ſaid, that if St. <hi>Francis</hi> had really received from God the marks of the wounds of Jeſus Chriſt, every one muſt needs have ſeen them, during the ſpace of thoſe two years, ſeing he went with his feet naked, and wore no gloves: but that none ever ſaw them, ſave one Fryar, named <hi>Elias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antonin. Tit. <hi>24.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> S. <hi>8.</hi> Solus hoc frater Elias caſu utcunque proſpicere meruit.</note> who ſaw them but once, and that by chance too. They ſaid alſo, that the miracles of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſerved to ſome good purpoſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to cure diſeaſes, to give eaſe and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the afflicted, to raiſe the dead <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that the marks of theſe wounds d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no cure at all, and are good for nothing That it is not credible, that God would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print theſe marks on a mortal body, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was ſoon after to putrifie, by which putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction theſe marks had been defaced Moreover, that although theſe marks had been really imprinted, yet it is a thing which the Devil, or men may eaſily coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:31684:41"/> That the Apoſtles, who had more worth in them then St. <hi>Francis,</hi> never had theſe marks.</p>
               <p>But the Pope interpoſed, and in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the ſervices which Brother <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> had done him, (for he was a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Popes Authority) Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed him, and put him in the Catalogue of the Saints. This Canonization was <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1228. Moreover, Pope <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1254. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that St. <hi>Francis</hi> was on Mount <hi>Alverno</hi> when he received the impreſſion of theſe wounds, took this occaſion to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Revenue: For he declared, that all the Eccleſiaſtical Lands and Goods in that Mountain did belong to the Pope, and were directy and immediately ſubject to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Moreover,<note place="margin">Antonin. cap. <hi>2.</hi> ſ. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> he did perſonally cite, and adjourn thoſe who had maliciouſly defaced the marks of the Image of S. <hi>Francis</hi> which was at <hi>Gennes,</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>Mary de Vignes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About twenty ſix years ſince, Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas</hi> the Fourth ſent Bulls to all the Churches under the Papal juriſdiction, certifying the truth of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s marks (though divers, who were hard of belief,<note place="margin">Antonin. pag. <hi>720.</hi>
                  </note> laughed at it:) ſince which time, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:31684:42"/> of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s marks is ſacred in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which (as <hi>Antonine</hi> ſaith) obſerves the Feaſt of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s marks; which honour is not done to the marks of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I conſider theſe things, I cannot enough wonder at the blindneſs of thoſe that give credit to things ſo full of abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and impoſtures: It ſeems as if the adorers of St. <hi>Francis</hi> had invented them on purpoſe to diſhonour and mock him; for no man, who hath any common ſenſe left him, will do ſuch things as are attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to St. <hi>Francis;</hi> who play'd the mad-man, that he might be counted a Saint; and, as much as in him lay, kept himſelf from the uſual and ordinary actions of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that he might be admired, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To draw roaſted fleſh through the aſhes; to wallow in the dirt with Swine; to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſnow; to give inſtruction to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals, and to call them his brethren and Siſters, are things which cannot be done by a man that is in his right ſenſes.</p>
               <p>And herein we muſt admire the juſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods diſpleaſure, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged the contempt of his Word contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the holy Scriptures; for in thoſe days, and in the following Ages, the holy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:31684:42"/> Scripture was a Book ſealed, and altogether unknown to the people: Nothing was then talked of, but Images, lying Wonders, Croiſades, Indulgences, adoration of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and the power of the Pope was then at the height, and abſurd and feigned Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends were the ordinary ſubject of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. Wherefore God being provoked, ſtrook the people with the ſpirit of giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and with a horrible blindneſs, which grew thicker and thicker, until God took the Candle of his Word from under the Buſhel, and expoſed to view the holy Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:31684:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> That under the Cloak of Humility Saint <hi>Francis</hi> hid an unparallel'd pride.</head>
               <p>WHoſoever ſhall rightly conſider the actions of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſhall under the Cloak of Humility diſcover an unparallel'd pride.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the Legend written by <hi>James de Voragine,</hi> it is reported, That <hi>Francis</hi> being priſoner with divers other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, he onely was merry, and all the reſt were ſad. And being asked what was the cauſe of his mirth, he anſwered; <hi>Ideo me exultare noveritis, quia adhuc ſanctus per totum ſeculum adorabar,</hi> that is, <hi>Know, that I rejoyce becauſe I ſhall be adored for a Saint throughout the World.</hi> To deſire to be adored is the higheſt degree of pride: None of the Apoſtles deſired this honour. <hi>Cornelius</hi> the <hi>Centurion,</hi> who was a man fearing God, knew that there is but one God, which he continually invoked; He knew well enough that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was not the Creator of the world: but being ſeized with reverence, he would have given him ſome inferiour adoration; for which St. <hi>Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:31684:43"/> him, ſaying. <hi>Stand up; I my ſelf alſo am a man. Act.</hi> 10.26. St. <hi>John,</hi> ſeized with fear, would have adored the Angel that talked with him, as you may ſee in the one and twentieth Chapter of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> But the Angel rebuked him, ſaying, <hi>See thou do it not, for I am thy fellow-ſervant; worſhip God.</hi> He knew well enough that this Angel was not God; for the ſame Angel had told him ſo before, in chap. 19 of the ſame book. Is it not therefore an impious folly, for a man to live the life of a begger, that he may be adored after his death?</p>
               <p>The Rule of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> which ſpeaks with an abſolute authority, demonſtrates the pride of him that compoſed it. For who gave brother <hi>Francis,</hi> who was of the meaneſt of the people, and without any charge either Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to compoſe laws different from the laws of God, and to make ordinances which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige men upon pain of damnation? Who gave him power to command with abſolute authority? For ſee how he ſpeaks in his Rule. <hi>Per obedientiam injungo Miniſtris; I enjoin Miniſters by their obedience.</hi> And he concludes his Rule with theſe words, <hi>That it is not lawfull for any man to infringe this Rule, or by raſh boldneſs to contradict it.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:31684:44"/> That if any one ſhall preſume to make ſuch an attempt, let him know, that he ſhall incur the diſpleaſure of Almighty God, and of the Bleſſed Apoſtles,</hi> Peter, <hi>and</hi> Paul.</p>
               <p>I demand how we can be aſſured that God would have us, upon pain of incurring his diſpleaſure, entirely obſerve the Rule of <hi>Francis d'Aſſiſe,</hi> and that God would be angry with a <hi>Minor</hi> Fryar, who, inſtead of a Cord, ſhould gird himſelf with a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-girdle, or ſhould receive mony, or would not wear patcht clothes, or would wear a ſhirt, or ſhould (whether he be a <hi>Capucin</hi> or a Lay <hi>Cordelier</hi>) ſay leſs then ſeventy ſix <hi>Paters</hi> in one day? What can be ſaid more againſt murtherers, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, and blaſphemers, than to ſay, that they incur the indignation of Almighty God? Hath not weak and ſinfull man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do to obey the commands of God, without having heavy burthens impoſed on him in things unneceſſary, and which God requires not, and then to be made believe, that he who doth in the leaſt tranſgreſs theſe laws, invented by man, doth incur the indignation of God?</p>
               <p>It is obſervable, that many of thoſe who are rigid obſervers of thoſe humane laws, and oblige others to be ſo too, do very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:31684:44"/> diſpence with the Laws of God; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e far from loving God with all their hearts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd their neighbors as themſelves.</p>
               <p>But ſuperſtition prevails more than Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gion. And hence it is that in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents of Monks there are envies, factions and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontinual emulations, beſides other vices.</p>
               <p>But how did this <hi>Francis d' Aſſiſe</hi> know, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat a Monk who obſerves not his Rule, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs the indignation of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul?</hi> Had he ſpoken with them? Did they declare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd promiſe that they would be avengers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd enemies to all thoſe that ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emn the Rule of the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars? We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave the Epiſtles of thoſe excellent Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tles, <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> which (without a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ompariſon) are better then St. <hi>Francis's</hi> Rule, and yet they do not declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elves avengers of the contempt of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octrines.</p>
               <p>They do not ſay, that he who ſhall vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate their precepts, ſhall incur their indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion. Wherefore it appears that this vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able <hi>Francis</hi> aſſumes an authority over the Apoſtles, whom he would oblige to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry for his ſake, and to undertake his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el. But it is not credible, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who enjoy celeſtial glory, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ern themſelves for the obſervation of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:31684:45"/> Rules of Monks, eſpecially ſeeing they themſelves were no Monks, and that their lives were as much unlike the lives of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucins,</hi> as heaven is diſtant from earth; Alſo becauſe there were no Convents of Monks in the Apoſtles days, nor in many ages after.</p>
               <p>Methinks it is enough to have <hi>God</hi> our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: If a man incurs the indignation of God, the indignation of theſe two Apoſtles wil not render him the more miſerable. In vain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth <hi>Francis,</hi> after he hath denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars, who ſhall diſobey his Rule, the indignation of God, threaten them with the indignation of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who are preſuppoſed (though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proof, and contrary to the word of God) to know the heart, and to ſee all that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> done here below.</p>
               <p>Alſo we would fain know, why <hi>Francis d' Aſſiſe</hi> threatens the Monks with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> onely? And why not with the indignation of St. <hi>John,</hi> and St. <hi>James?</hi> But perhaps he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that they have leſs credit in heaven, or that they are leſs cholerick.</p>
               <p>It is very obſervable, that <hi>Francis d'Aſſiſe</hi> compoſed his Rule (wherein he gives laws, and commandeth with authority,) when he was but a Lay man, and a private perſon, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:31684:45"/> a long time before the Pope approved it: And although he was of the meaneſt rank of people, and without any office or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet he ſpeaks magiſterially.</p>
               <p>To the Rule of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> is added his Teſtament, wherein he ſpeaks with full power, and authority, ſaying, <hi>Firmiter volo quod fratres laborent de laboritio, &amp; praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio firmiter fratribus per obedientiam,</hi> &amp;c. That is, <hi>I do ſtrictly charge, and do firmly, and abſolutely command the Fryars by their obedience, &amp;c.</hi> He preſuppoſeth, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is due to him, and that his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ought to be firm, and inviolable. Kings ſpeak not with more authority.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:31684:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Some Laws and Ordinances contained in St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Rule.</head>
               <p>THe Rule of <hi>Francis d'Aſſiſe</hi> begins with theſe words:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Rule and Life of the</hi> Minor <hi>Fryars is as follows,</hi> viz. <hi>to obſerve the holy Goſpel of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in theſe things,</hi> viz. <hi>in living Obediently, Chaſtly, and without Property.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe words are very remarkable; for they do not oblige the Monks to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> to be the eternal Son of God, and the Saviour and Redeemer of the world, nor to be charitable and liberal to the poor, nor to be at peace with their neighbours, nor to do to others what they would have done to themſelves, nor dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to read the holy Scripture, and to be inſtructed in the Doctrine of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which are things expreſly contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and recommended by the Apoſtles: But
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:31684:46"/> this Rule obligeth the <hi>Minor,</hi> Fryars to obſerve the Goſpel in things which the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> commands not; for you cannot find, that the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> forbids any one to marry; on the contrary, <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> by the mouth of his Apoſtle, commands thoſe who cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to marry, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> was married. <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> forbids us not to poſſeſs any thing in particular, nor doth he command us to live in beggery by the ſweat of other mens brows. He commands not to make a Vow of Obedience to a Guardian, or Abbot, or Superiour of a Monaſtery; for in the dayes of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> there were no ſuch people, nor in many Ages after. Can there be a more manifeſt mockery, then to oblige men by Vow to obey the Goſpel in ſuch things whereof the Goſpel makes not the leaſt mention, and ſome whereof are contrary to the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>But if theſe things are commanded in the Goſpel, (as this Rule falſly preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,) why then doth the Pope diſpence with this Vow, by permitting Monks to marry? However, he ſeldome gives this permiſſion, except to perſons of great Quality.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:31684:47"/>
               <p>In the ſecond Chapter of the ſame Rule, you ſhall find theſe words:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let thoſe who are received Monks, have a Cloak with a Hood, and (if they will) another without a Hood. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, let thoſe wear ſhooes, who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by neceſſity ſo to do. Likewiſe, let all the Fryars wear poor and baſe cloathes, which they may patch with pieces of ſack-cloth and ſuch other ſtuff, and ſhall have the bleſſing of God with it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Muſt not that man be out of his wits, who thinks, that the patching of old cloathes can bring down the bleſſing of God upon any one? And ſeeing the <hi>Capucins</hi> cloathes are of woollen-cloth, St. <hi>Francis</hi> did very improperly ordain, that they ſhould be patched with ſack-cloth.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Chapter of this Rule, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of three Lents, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lent before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> another from <hi>All Saints</hi> day till <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> and the other from the day of the <hi>Epiphany</hi> till the Lent before
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:31684:47"/> 
                  <hi>Eaſter.</hi> So that there are five Months of Lent: The two firſt are neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, but the third is left to every ones liberty.</p>
               <p>In this ſame Chapter, the <hi>Minor</hi> Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars are forbiden to ride on Horſe-back, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in caſe of extreme neceſſity. Alſo they are commanded, when they enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any houſe, to eat whatſoever is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. By this Rule, they may eat fleſh in Lent.</p>
               <p>They are likewiſe forbidden, in the ſame Chapter, to receive money, either perſonally, or by Proxie: For Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas</hi> hath already told us, that to have a Bag, and Money, as <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles had, is an action of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: but Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> who had neither Bag nor Money, attained unto greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
               <p>In the fifth Chapter of the ſame Rule, <hi>Francis d'Aſſiſe</hi> commands his Monks to labour with their hands, if they are able: But in his Teſtament he ſpeake more preciſely; for he ſaith, that he himſelf did labour with his hands; and he adds,</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:31684:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I do likewiſe expreſly command all the other Monks to labour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>This Command is not obſerved now a dayes; for the <hi>Capucins</hi> and <hi>Cordeliers</hi> who underſtand a Trade, had rather live in idle beggery by other mens labour: And thus they daily break their Vow, and tranſgreſs their Rule.</p>
               <p>But above all are remarkable the words of the Tenth Chapter of this Rule, which are theſe;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let not the Fryars trouble themſelves to teach thoſe to read, who cannot read; but above all things let them deſire the Spirit of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>St. <hi>Francis</hi> ſayes this, becauſe ſome Monks are very ignorant, and cannot read. Some ſuch there are now adayes, but not ſo many as there were in St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s time; whoſe opinion it is, That no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy needs trouble himſelf to teach them to read, that ſo they may be inſtructed in the holy Scriptures; he had rather
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:31684:48"/> they ſhould remain ignorant: Onely he would have them deſire the Holy Ghoſt; not conſidering, that God gives this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to thoſe who are inſtructed in his Word: For, to deſire the Holy Spirit, and yet to neglect the ordinary means whereby the Holy Spirit works in the hearts of men, is to ſhut the door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, while we deſire him; it is juſt as if a man ſhould deſire to have a Bell rung, without having the Clapper of it moved.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Commands of <hi>Francis d'Aſſiſe,</hi> who is exalted above the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins that ſtand before the Throne of God; to the obſervation of which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, he promiſeth Life Eternal; and by the tranſgreſſion of them, a man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs the indignation of God, and of the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> but not of St. <hi>Philip,</hi> and St. <hi>Luke.</hi> Moreover, here are better and more excellent things propoſed, then thoſe which God commands in his Law, <hi>viz.</hi> Works of Supererogation, which merit a ſuper-eminent degree of Glory, far above the ordinary ſort of Saints, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented themſelves with doing what God commands.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:31684:49"/>
               <p>To this Rule are added the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Order; (whereof I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken:) which the <hi>Capucins</hi> obſerve more exactly, and with greater obedience then they do the Law of God, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:31684:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> That the Holy Scripture is falſified and wreſted in the Rule of St. <hi>Francis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have heard before, that St. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure</hi> ſaith, That St. <hi>Franci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had not any ſcience acquired by ſtudy; but that he had received the knowledge of the Holy Scriptures by divine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Whether this be true or not, will appear by the paſſages of Scripture, which <hi>Francis d' Aſſiſe</hi> alledgeth in his Rule.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Chapter, he ſtrictly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars to forſake the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but will have them continue in it as long as they live: And that they ought ſo to do, he proves by a paſſage of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> in his Ninth Chapter, Verſe 62. where <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>No man having put his hand to the plough, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back, is fit for the Kingdome of God.</hi> The connexion of this paſſage with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Verſes, ſhews, that by him who puts his hand to the plough, and looks back, is meant ſuch a one whom <hi>Jeſus
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:31684:50"/> Christ</hi> having ſent to preach the Goſpel, and having undertaken that charge, doth afterwards leave it to ſerve his worldly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. Our Lord ſpeaks not of him who hath vowed never to marry, and to wear no ſhirt, and to live by begging, and to obſerve humane Rules and Traditions, which enſnare men in unclean luſts, and which are given to God for better works then thoſe commanded in his Law, as if Man would make him a debtor. In a word, to forſake the ſervice of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and to tranſgreſs the Rule of <hi>Francis d' Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſe,</hi> is, in his opinion, one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>In the Ninth Chapter of the ſame Rule, St. <hi>Francis</hi> commands the Monks to be brief in their Sermons, <hi>Quia verbum ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviatum fecit Dominus ſuper terram;</hi> that is, <hi>Becauſe the Lord made his word ſhort upon earth:</hi> Which is a paſſage taken from the Tenth Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Verſ. 23. and from the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 9, Verſ. 28. where is no mention at all made of Sermons or words which men pronounce with their mouthes; but of Gods judgments and puniſhments, which he haſteneth, and will ſpeedily bring
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:31684:50"/> upon men. The divine inſpiration given to St. <hi>Francis</hi> did not (it ſeems) teach him, that as well in the Old as New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Verbum</hi> is very often taken for <hi>Res</hi> or <hi>Negotium;</hi> as in <hi>Exodus.</hi> Chap. 2. Verſ. 14. and Chap. 9. Verſ. 5, &amp; 6. and in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 4. and Chap. 2. Verſ. 6. and in St. <hi>Luke,</hi> Chap. 1. Verſ. 37. and Chap. 2. Verſ. 15. and often elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:31684:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of Poverty, and riches.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRancis d' Aſſiſe</hi> made profeſſion to be a great lover of Poverty, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called it his Miſtreſs. In his Rule he ſpeaks thus to his Monks; <hi>It is this ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of moſt lofty poverty (my dear bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) which makes you heires, and Kings of the Kingdom of Heaven, and exalts you in vertues, who are poor in ſubſtance:</hi> And thereupon he forbids them to poſſeſs any thing of all that is under the Sun.</p>
               <p>He himſelf put this Rule in practice. For having a competent eſtate, he left it all: yea he left his breeches, and the reſt of his clothes, and went about ſtark naked.</p>
               <p>As for Poverty in general, many take delight in prayſing it; yea, thoſe very perſons who ſhun it; And to extoll it, they ſay that Jeſus Chriſt was poore: But that ſerves rather to ſhew that pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is an evil; for Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to bear our infirmities, and to ſuſtaine our ſorrows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> in the 45. Chapter of his book
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:31684:51"/> 
                  <hi>of the Monks,</hi> ſaith, that Jeſus Chriſt was a begger. To the titles of the Son of God, the Redeemer, the Word, the Wiſdom of the Father, nothing was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to compleat his prayſes, but to call him begger: But a man cannot properly be ſaid to be a begger for living by the help and aſſiſtance of another.</p>
               <p>We may judg of the nature of riches, and poverty by this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that God is infinitely rich, and that the Devil is the pooreſt of all creatures. Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, that it is better to give then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; intimating thereby, that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a man to give what he hath, then to aske what he hath not; For he that gives, imitates God, who gives alwayes, but receives never. Liberality is alwayes better then indigence: It is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable to give then to receive an almes. And certainly, he that blames riches as evil in their own nature, blames God, who is the Author of them, and diſtributes them as it pleaſeth him. God oftentimes exhorts his people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to piety by the promiſes of temporal good things. And <hi>Solomon</hi> asking of him Wiſdom onely, he gave him riches alſo, without parallel.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:31684:52"/>
               <p>St <hi>James</hi> indeed ſaith, <hi>that God hath choſen the poor;</hi> but he adds, <hi>that are rich in faith.</hi> For the happineſs of theſe Poor conſiſts not in their being poor, but in their being rich in faith. Thus muſt we underſtand what Jeſus Chriſt ſaith in the ſixth Chapter of <hi>St. Luke, Bleſſed be ye poor.</hi> For that which makes a poor man happy, is not his poverty, but the manner of ſupporting his poverty. There be rich men that are very vertuous; and poor men that are very wicked, whom poverty excites to theft, murther, perjury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Agur,</hi> in the Thirtieth Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> deſires of God, not to ſend him poverty. The Soul of poor Lazarus is carried by Angels into the boſom of rich <hi>Abraham.</hi> So that the poor and rich are put together, to teach us, that rich as well as poor are received into the Kingdom of God, if they fear and ſerve him according to his word.</p>
               <p>It is true indeed, that riches do corrupt many, and ſerve onely to puff them up with pride, to enflame their luſts, and to divert their hearts from truſting in God, to truſt in their riches. And this is the reaſon why Jeſus Chriſt ſaith that it is hard for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:31684:52"/> a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God: But this evil proceeds not from riches, but from thoſe that abuſe them, into whoſe lap riches falling are corrupted, as a Crown is defiled that fals into a puddle, and in whoſe hands the goods of this world are like a ſword in the hands of a mad-man. We muſt not believe that Jeſus Chriſt in the 16th. Chapter of St. <hi>Luke</hi> calls riches <hi>unrighteous,</hi> becauſe there is any unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the poſſeſſing of them, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are gotten by unrighteous means, but becauſe they are either provocations, or inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs, to thoſe that are deſtitute of the fear of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:31684:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> Of the vow of poverty, and of idle begging: Alſo of works, and ſatisfactions of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation.</head>
               <p>THere are two ſorts of poverty: one which God ſends, and another to which men do voluntarily devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without Gods ſending it unto them. The former is an affliction, the other is a direct profeſſion, which ſome chooſe, as ſuppoſing it of great merit, and a work of ſupererogation. There be ſome poor, whom God hath reduced to a low eſtate, wherein they get a ſlender livelyhood by the labour of their hands: who, if they be contented with their conditions, and by ſerving God with a pure Conſcience, do aſpire to better riches, <hi>viz.</hi> the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are happy, and beloved of God, and truly rich. There be others, whom God bereaves of their eſtates for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpel, who, although they have not purpoſely drawn poverty on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet, if they bear this yoke pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently and joyfully, eſteeming it an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:31684:53"/> to bear the Croſs of Chriſt, their pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y may be ſaid to be voluntary, becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oluntarily follow the call of God. Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſe Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks in the ninth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hapter of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Who have left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather, mother, wife, children, or lands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or his ſake; God having reduced them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſuch a neceſſity, that they cannot keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir eſtates without forſaking the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſion of the Goſpel. In this caſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e muſt lay down our very lives, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive our ſouls; and muſt be prodigal of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur eſtate to be niggardly of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</p>
               <p>But there is an affected poverty, which ſome embrace, by vow, and without any neceſſity, or God's obliging of them thereunto; who may keep their eſtates with a good conſcience, but yet had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her leave them to live by other men's eſtates, and had rather beg than work. This poverty is a yoke which God impoſeth not on them, but they impoſe it on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They bear not Chriſt's croſs, but their own. They leave the exerciſe of charity, upon pretence of humility and patience. It may be ſaid, that they are like the fowls of the air, for they ſow not,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:31684:54"/> neither do they reap, and yet their fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Pope, feeds them plentifully: for w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee, that thoſe who have vowed poverty are fat, and plump; and though they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor in particular, yet are they rich i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> common. They get more by begging thou the common people do by working<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Many turn Monks in ſpight, or to ſhak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> off the yoke of their parents, or in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and deſperate humour, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud their creditors, who preſs hard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, or becauſe they will not take pains to work, or have not wherewith to ſubſiſt at home. They turn beggers, that they may not be poor. They are poor by vow, for fear of being ſo by neceſſity. Wherefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeaks very grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his cap. <hi>46.</hi> ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</note> when he ſaith, That to theſe beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Monks belongs that ſaying of Jeſus Chriſt, in the nineteenth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew, Centuplum accipiet, &amp;c.</hi> That is, <hi>He ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inherit eternal life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when our adverſaries call begging a a work of ſupererogation, they do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by acknowledg, that God commands it not. The Prophets, and Apoſtles never vowed poverty, neither were they beggars.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:31684:54"/> Thoſe of them who were poor, were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o by vow, but by neceſſity, which God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpoſed on them.<note place="margin">Joh. 21.3. Joh. 19.27. Phil. 4.16</note> The Apoſtles had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Fiſhing Veſſels after our Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urrection; And St. <hi>John</hi> had his houſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>Paul</hi> received with thankfulneſs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ief which the <hi>Philippians</hi> ſent him: Being at <hi>Corinth,</hi> he got his living by making of Tents, chooſing rather to work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han to beg; For he well knew, that beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing is a ſhamefull thing, and that it makes men both idle and impudent. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat leaves his own eſtate, to eat ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her mans bread, hath no reaſon to ſay to God, <hi>Give us this day our dayly bread;</hi> For God might anſwer him, <hi>I gave thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herewith to buy bread, but thou haſt deſpiſed it; And now by thy beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, thou takeſt from them that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eally poor, thoſe Almes which are due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo far is begging from being a work of ſupererogation, and better then what God commands in his Law, that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the contrary, God will have us pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it as much as we can,<note place="margin">Omnino non erit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiens &amp; mendicus inter vos.</note> ſaying in <hi>Deut.</hi> chap 15. verſe. 4. <hi>To the end that there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay be no poor among you.</hi> The Hebrew
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:31684:55"/> word ſignifies a <hi>Beggar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and the Vulga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tranſlation ſo renders it. Not that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſin to beg, when a man hath no other wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſubſiſtence: But God commands, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rich ſo to relieve the poor, that they ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not be conſtrained to beg.</p>
               <p>The Scripture often ſpeaks of beggin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as an evil, and a puniſhment, yea, a curſe In the ſeven and thirtieth <hi>Pſalm, Davi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſaith, <hi>I have been young, and now am ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yet have I not ſeen the righteous forſake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nor his ſeed begging bread.</hi> And in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 109. <hi>Pſalm</hi> he makes this imprecation <hi>Let his Children be vagabonds, and beg</hi> He ſpeaks indeed of involuntary poverty but there is no likelyhood, that that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a curſe to ſome, can be a bleſſing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others; and that which to one is a grie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vous affliction, can be to another a hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>As for examples, we have already ſee the deſcription which <hi>Lucian</hi> and <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leius</hi> give of the Prieſts of the <hi>Syrian</hi> go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſs, who did whip themſelves, and beg To which we ſhall adde the <hi>Maſſali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Heretiques,<note place="margin">Epiphan. haeret. <hi>80.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> of whom <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith <hi>they went about begging, as not havin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wherewith to ſubſiſt, neither poſſeſſing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:31684:55"/>
               <p>Examine Antiquity, and try if you can find ſo much as one example of Monks that made begging a Profeſſion. There was no ſuch thing as a Profeſſion of beggary, for abovte welve hundred years after the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of our Lord. <hi>Camus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bellay,</hi> who is yet living, hath written a great book <hi>of the labours of Monks;</hi> in the Preface whereof you ſhall find theſe words; <hi>The ulcer of idleneſs is crept into Monaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, under the name of holy und meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beggary.</hi> His whole book is imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prove that Monks ſhould be obliged to labour with their hands, eſpecially thoſe that do not preach, nor have any other painfull employment in the Church: So far is he from placing beggary amongſt thoſe pieces of perfection, whereby God is made a debtor to man. And this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late's book bears in its front, the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Doctors of the faculty of <hi>Theologie</hi> of <hi>Paris.</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a book <hi>De opere Monachorum,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he obligeth them to labor. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> teacheth the ſame, in <hi>the Hereſie of the Maſſalians;</hi> where, he ſaith, that in all the Monaſteries of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Monkes did labour with their hands, even as Bees
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:31684:56"/> do labor to make hony and wax. In thoſe days the Monks were poor Hermits, living in deſerts, labouring with their hands to get their living, and carrying their work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip to the neighbouring Towns to ſell, bought bread with the mony: They did not beg the approbation of their Rule from the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for they were not ſubject to him; In a word, they were not at all like the Monks now adays. The ſame <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in the ſame book, condemns thoſe that live an idle life, and making a profeſſion of begging, get their bread at rich men's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>But to compleat their wickedneſs, the mendicant Fryars make begging a work of ſupererogation, that is, better than what God commands in his Law, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, better than to love God with all our hearts, and our neighbour as our ſelves. God commands us to ſerve him with all our ſtrength, ſo that the Monks ſerve God with more then all their ſtrength, which is impoſſible. <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob, Samuel, David, &amp;c.</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did works of ſupererogation. The perfection of the Angels conſiſts in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:31684:56"/> God, and not in doing more than he commands. Jeſus Chriſt himſelf came into the world onely to do the will of his Father, and not to do more then his will. Aske the moſt devout <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucin,</hi> if he never commits ſin; and he will tell you, that he is a poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: How do theſe things agree? They do not that which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and yet will do more then he commands! They fail in neceſſary things, and yet ſtrive to do things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, and which God requires not! They do not what they ought, and do what they ought not! They are more holy than God would have them to be!</p>
               <p>That man is crack-braind, who exerciſeth liberality when he hath not wherewith to pay his debts: If this be ſo in referrence to men, how much more in reference to God? It is an extream pride, to endeavour to give God overplus, and more then we owe him.</p>
               <p>In a word, I would know whether the Monks, when they do works of ſupererogation, do the will of God, or
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:31684:57"/> their own will. If they do the will of God, they are obliged thereunto, and do what they ought: But if, by doing better things then thoſe which God commands, they do their own will, it follows that their will is better than the will of God.</p>
               <p>Out of this ſame ſhop of pride, come thoſe ſuperabundant ſatisfactions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Monks would make us believe, that they ſuffer more puniſhment, and do more pennance, then their ſinnes deſerve, and that the Pope gathers this overplus into his Treaſury, and diſtributes it by his Indulgences in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſins of others. The Monks believe, that by whipping them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by faſting and going bare-foot, they expiate the ſinnes of others: Wherefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Bell. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Indul. r. <hi>4.</hi> ſ. ſex.</note> that the Saints are, in ſome ſenſe, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers. The Legends of Saint <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick</hi> and Saint <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſay, that Saint <hi>Dominick,</hi> a grand emulator of the holineſs of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> laſht himſelf three times a day with an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron chain, <hi>viz.</hi> Once for his own ſins, which were very ſmall, once for the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:31684:57"/> ſinnes of the living, and once for the ſinnes of thoſe ſouls which are in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, who (no doubt) received much eaſe thereby. And it is this ſame Saint, that once had mercy on the devil: for the devil having tranſform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf into a Sparrow, and Saint <hi>Dominick</hi> catching him, contented himſelf onely with pulling off the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from his head, whereas it was in his power to have wrung off his neck.</p>
               <p>By theſe things God is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: For ſuch things are attributed to God, which if a man ſhould do, he would be accounted either wicked, or mad. For, what Judge would not be accounted unjuſt, or out of his wits, who ſhould let a malefactor go, becauſe his neighbour hath whipt himſelf for him? But things which are ridiculous in civil ſociety, are eſteemed good in religion; as if a man muſt loſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe to augment piety.</p>
               <p>All this abuſe proceeds from this, <hi>viz.</hi> that men, utterly deſtitute of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the holy Scriptures, which are to them a book ſealed, and altogether
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:31684:58"/> unknown, ſeek other ſatisfactions, and other payments for ſin, then the death and paſſion of Jeſus Chriſt. For ſeeing Jeſus Chriſt hath fully ſatisfied Gods juſtice, to what purpoſe are others ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions preſented to him? Is not this to accuſe God of injuſtice, to pretend that he takes two payments for one debt, when the firſt is ſufficient? Is it not to diſhonour that moſt perfect ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, which Jeſus Chriſt hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed for us, to joyn it with the whippings and auſterities of Monks; which is juſt as if a man ſhould mingle coals and diamonds together? For Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the VI. in his Extravagant <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitus,</hi> ſaith, that the merits of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of the other Saints, do help to compleat the treaſure of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Jeſus Chriſt; giving us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the benefits of Jeſus Chriſt make but bare meaſure; but that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Saints merits makes heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meaſure, and is an addition to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus Chriſt. And for this reaſon, the Prieſt in the Maſs prays for ſalvation, not onely through the Saints interceſſion, but alſo through their merits.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:31684:58"/>
               <p>The Lord God, take pity on ſo many poor people involved in ſo many abuſes, and diſcover the deceit of thoſe who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves notorious ſinners, do yet by a proud humility think to expiate the ſins of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:31684:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> Of the Fraternity of the <hi>Cord.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Printed at <hi>Rouen</hi> by <hi>Tho. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ré,</hi> in the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtreet, near the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, <hi>anno</hi> 1614.</note> An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of a Book, entituled <hi>The Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Indulgences of St.</hi> Francis<hi>'s Cord,</hi> tranſlated out of <hi>Italian</hi> into <hi>French:</hi> And of the Canonization of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius de Loyola.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Fraternity of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Cord, is a Society of ſuperſtitiouſly devout people, both Men and Women, and as well Clergy-men as Lay-men: Into which Fraternity they who enter, are obliged to certain Obſervations, and for a Badge of the Fraternity wear a Cord, in imitation of the Cord which St. <hi>Francis</hi> wore, and do participate of all the Merits and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions of thoſe of the ſaid Fraternity. They who have the leaſt of merit, do, for all that, as really partake of the merits of the others, as if they were their own: They lend their merits to each other; and he that is aſleep, or at dinner, partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates of the merits of him that whips himſelf, or of him that turns over the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:31684:59"/> conſecrated Beads of his Chaplet ſeven times.</p>
               <p>The Fraternity of Saint <hi>Francis</hi>'s Cord hath great Priviledges, and the Popes have granted it great Indulgences. Theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges have been ſet down in writing by divers, but eſpecially by <hi>Antonio Brugneto,</hi> an <hi>Italian Obſervantin</hi> Monk, whoſe very words in the 104. page are theſe;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The moſt glorious Father</hi> Francis, <hi>a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before his death, obtained of God the Creator three Priviledges, as the defunct Pope</hi> Gregory <hi>reports them from St.</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis <hi>his own mouth,</hi> viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt is, That as the number of Monks ſhould increaſe, ſo ſhould all things neceſſary be provided for them by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſecond, That whoſoever ſhall wear the Habi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of his Order, ſhall not die un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third, That whoſoever ſhall perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Religion of his Order, his dayes ſhall be ſhort, and his end miſerable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moreover, the moſt glorious Father</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, <hi>a little before his death, revealed to a certain Monk (who is worthy of credit)
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:31684:60"/> that he had obtained three other Priviledges of our Creator, when he appeared to him in the likeneſs of a Seraphin, and left the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the holy Marks on him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt is, That the profeffion of his Monks ſhould continue until the end of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſecond, That whoſoever ſhall live well in his Order, ſhall live a long time in it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third, That whoſoever ſhall hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love his Order, how great a ſinner ſoever he be, ſhall find mercy from God, if ſo be he turns from his evil wayes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>The ſame Author in the 109. page hath theſe words;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt, Pope</hi> Clement <hi>the Fourth hath granted to thoſe men, who on their death-beds ſhall deſire to be clad in the Habit of St.</hi> Francis <hi>his Order; and to thoſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who ſhall deſire to be clad in the Habit of St.</hi> Clare, <hi>and to be buried in it, the pardon of the third part of their ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This ſame Indulgence was granted them by Pope</hi> Nicolas <hi>the Third, and by Pope</hi> Urban <hi>the Fifth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:31684:60"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moreover, Pope</hi> Leo <hi>the Tenth, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Conceſſions, adds by way of overplus, That they who ſhould die in this Habit of St.</hi> Francis, <hi>or St.</hi> Clare, <hi>and ſhould be buried therein, ſhould have a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence for all their ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>And in the 95. page;</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moreover, on Olive-Saturday, on the Feaſt of St.</hi> John <hi>the Evangelist, and on the other Feast of St.</hi> John Port-Latine, (<hi>Pope</hi> Sixtus <hi>the Fifth,) he hath granted to thoſe of the Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, who ſhall on ſuch dayes rehearſe the ſeven Penitentiary Pſalms, the redemption of one Soul out of Purgatory.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>As for the Indulgence granted (as the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars ſay) by Jeſus Chriſt, and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and confirmed by the Pope at <hi>Noſtre Dame des Anges,</hi> called <hi>Portiuncula;</hi> the Roſary of <hi>Bernardin,</hi> and the aforeſaid book of rhe Indulgences of the Cord, and the Chronicle of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſay, that St. <hi>Francis</hi> would not have the Pope's Bull for confirmation of the ſaid Indulgence: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have the glorious Virgin, and Jeſus Chriſt for Notaries, and the Angels for Witneſſes.</hi> This Indulgence is to be had on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:31684:61"/> day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> whereby every one who hath been confeſſed, and is contrite, and ſhall then go into the Church of <hi>Noſtre Dame des Anges,</hi> ſhall obtaine a plenary abſolution both of ſin, and puniſhment. If this ſame perſon ſhould go into any other Church with the like or greater contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſhould not have the ſame Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. It is worth our notice, that St. <hi>Francis</hi> obtained this Indulgence of Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> by preſenting him with three red Roſes in the Winter.</p>
               <p>But Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth, who was a <hi>Cordelier,</hi> hath abundantly heaped up Indulgences, plenary, more plenary, and moſt plenary, (as they Phraſe it) on the Order of the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars, and upon the Fraternity of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s Cord.</p>
               <p>But of all theſe Indulgences, of three, or four hundred thouſand years, the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> make little reckoning, and have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver much troubled themſelves about pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing any of them from the Pope; eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their own Order, although bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in pardons, and Indulgences, better then that of the <hi>Minor</hi> Fryars.</p>
               <p>However, in one reſpect the <hi>Cordeliers,</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:31684:61"/> and <hi>Capucins</hi> ſurpaſs the Jeſuits, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in that St. <hi>Francis</hi> was Canonized by the Pope immediately after his death, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt difficulty: But as for <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the founder and Patron of the Jeſuits, who dyed <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1556, the Jeſuits were above ſeventy years ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> to obtaine from the Pope that he might be put into the number of the Saints; and at laſt, with great difficulty, obtained his Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation, ſeventy years after his death. So long did the ſanctity of <hi>Ignatius</hi> hang in ſuſpence; which, no doubt, was the cauſe of great trouble, and perplexity to him. However this future Saint, during all this waiting, received ſome conſolation; For, ſome years before his Canonization he was Beatified, which is a forerunner of Canonization.</p>
               <p>At laſt the Pope having received more clear and certain proofs of the holineſs of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> put him into the Catalogue of the Saints, and ordained that he ſhould be invoked in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which had not been lawful during thoſe ſeventy years that paſt betwixt <hi>Ignatius</hi> his death and Canonization.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:31684:62"/>
               <p>But as in the Chappels, and Colledges of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> you ſhall ſee few Images of St. <hi>Francis;</hi> ſo in the Convents, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Churches of the <hi>Capucins</hi> it is a very rar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing to ſee the image of St. <hi>Ignatiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> For the <hi>Capucins</hi> believe, that St. <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> hath more credit in the Court of heaven and that he is exalted above the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31684:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
